<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Saint Peters watch word the end of all things is at hand / digested into eight chapters, and published by R.M. minister ; perused and allowed.</title>
            <author>Mavericke, Radford, b. 1561?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 218 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07289</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17683A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S450</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22438743</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22438743</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25534</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07289)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25534)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1754:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Saint Peters watch word the end of all things is at hand / digested into eight chapters, and published by R.M. minister ; perused and allowed.</title>
                  <author>Mavericke, Radford, b. 1561?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 80 [i.e. 161) p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I.W. dwelling at Powles Wharfe, at the signe of the Crosse-keyes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K⁸ L⁶.</note>
                  <note>Pages numbered on recto only.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, stained, tightly bound and torn, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Peter, 1st, IV, 7 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25534:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25534:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SAINT PETERS WATCH <hi>WORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The end of all things is at hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Digeſted into eight Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and publiſhed by R.M. Minister.</p>
            <p>Peruſed and allowed.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Reuel. 22.7.</hi>
               </bibl> Behold I come ſhortly.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ver. 20.</hi>
               </bibl> Surely I come quickly.</q>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>I.W.</hi> dwelling at Powles <hi>Wharfe, at the ſigne of the Croſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keyes.</hi> 1603.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:25534:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Contents of euery ſeuerall Chapter in this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>IN the first Chapter, The Watchword it ſelfe is explained.</item>
               <item>In the ſecond, the day of Iudgement that it ſhall be, is proued.</item>
               <item>In the third, the names and titles of that day are noted.</item>
               <item>In the fourth, the ſignes and tokens of that day are remembred.</item>
               <item>In the fifth, who ſhall bee the ſupreme Iudge at that day is ſhewed.</item>
               <item>In the ſixt, the glorious comming of Christ vnto Iudgement is deciphered,</item>
               <item>In the ſeuenth, the order &amp; maner of the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is deſcribed.</item>
               <item>In the eight, an exhortation vnto prayer, ſobriety and watchfulneſſe is added, with a neceſſarie prayer annexed thereunto.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:25534:2"/>
            <head>TO THE VERIE VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull, vertuous, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Gentlewoman, Miſtreſſe <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Foord, wife vnto the worſhipfull ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Th. Foord</hi> of Ilſington in Deuonſhire <hi>Eſquire: R.M. dayly prayeth the rich bleſſings</hi> of God, to be powred down vpon them, their kindred and poſteritie, to their comforts in this life, and to their eternall ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in the life to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He dayes of man, being compared with eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, may be likened vnto one ſande on the Sea ſhore, vnto one graſſe vpon the ground, or to one ſtarre in the firmament, matched with all the reſt: for if a man coulde liue, as ſome almoſt haue liued, <hi>a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares,</hi> yet all thoſe yeares, are but <hi>as one day with God.</hi> The ignoraunce
<pb facs="tcp:25534:3"/>whereof, hath made men imagine, that it is a very long while agone ſince God created man; and that ſeeing the world hath continued ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares; therefore that it ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue an ende: yea the worſer ſort do thinke, that either God hath not at all determined to deſtroy this worlde; or, if he haue determined and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſo to do, that then he hath forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten his promiſe. And therefore ſay many times to themſelues, <hi>Where is the promiſe of Chriſt his comming,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come? And wherefore doth he make ſo long delay?</p>
            <p>Whereunto our Sauiour himſelfe doth anſwere, if we would vouchſafe to heare him; and ſweares becauſe we ſhoulde beleeue him: <hi>Beholde I come ſhortly:</hi> And, <hi>ſurely I come quickly,</hi> tary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for no mans pleaſure, one minute of an houre longer, then is determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and appoynted, which appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time, though no man may curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly inquire of; yet euery good Chriſtian wil dayly think of it, &amp; thank
<pb facs="tcp:25534:3"/>God, for any good thing that may put them in remembrance of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Among which number of true hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſtians, becauſe I knowe your worſhip to bee one, and ſuch a one whereof in my charge, I take greate comfort, as well for your godlineſſe, as for your kindneſſe extended vnto me; I therefore offer vnto your meeke Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, by way of dedication, theſe my poore labours (howſoeuer imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, or vnpoliſhed) which at times of leyſure, I haue collected ſince my firſt comming vnto you; through the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and preſentment of your kinde husband, and my very worſhipfull and louing Patron. Publiſhing the ſame in this ſort, for the benefite of all, but (through their owne fault) for the comfort onely of all ſuch, as either do, or hereafter ſhall vnfainedly loue and looke for the comming of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt to their immortalitie.</p>
            <p>Beſeeching the diuine maieſtie, to giue vs grace and patience, cheerfully to paſſe ouer this our pilgrimage in his
<pb facs="tcp:25534:4"/>feare, and in ſome diſcharge of our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in a good conſcience, to Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and to ſome good of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; howſoeuer the world, and the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof, ſhall eſteeme of vs or of any thing we do: that ſo at laſt to our endleſſe ioy, we may heare that ſweet ſentence of our ſauiour pronounced vnto vs, <hi>Euge bone ſerue &amp; fidelis: Well done good and faithfull ſeruant, thou haſt beene faithfull in few things, I will make thee ruler ouer much, enter thou into the ioy of thy Maiſter:</hi> Which God of his mercy grant, through the merit of his ſonne, by the aſſiſtance of Gods holy ſpirit; who ſeale the aſſurance therof in our hearts: to which holy and bleſſed Trinitie, be aſcribed all prayſe, power and maieſtie, for euer, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips as much bounden vnder God, as his life is worth; and in the Lord euer to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded.</hi> Radford Mauericke.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:25534:4"/>
            <head>To each Chriſtian <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, all health and eternall</hi> happineſſe wiſhed and deſired.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing more then one yeare paſſed (right courteous and Chriſtian Reader) ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence I was entreated to peruſe Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Chaine, for ſetting it on vnto a ſecond Edition; I therupon (by Gods helpe togither with that labour) tooke occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and courage to contriue this little work called <hi>Saint Peters watchworde;</hi> which may either paſſe alone by it ſelfe, or bee ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to that Chaine, according as it ſhall bee fitting and expedient: the mettall both of the one and the other, being fineſt golde of the trueſt touch; first hammered vpon the
<pb facs="tcp:25534:5"/>Anuill in Saint <hi>Peters</hi> forge, by that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle himſelfe, and whatſoeuer is added vnto it, and howſoeuer vnpoliſhed, yet you ſhall finde it weighed, I truſt, in the vpright ballance of the Lords Sanctuarie.</p>
            <p>Which Watchworde of the Apoſtle if it waken them that are ſound a ſleepe in ſinne; and warne them that are alreadie waking, to ſtand vpon their guard more warily then heretofore: it is the onely marke that I ayme at, and the verie bleſsing of God vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe poore and vnlaboured labours of mine, which I heartily deſire.</p>
            <p>And becauſe (as all men know) it is a very vnpleaſant thing, any whit to trouble them that are aſleepe: and euen breuitie it ſelfe to them that are napping, is counted tediouſneſſe: I haue therefore not onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured, to be as briefe as conueniently I might throughout this whole Treatiſe, that ſo I might not offende them that are beſt diſpoſed: but haue alſo cut or deuided this diſcourſe into diuerſe partes or Chapters; that ſo euen they that are drowſie, may at leaſt wiſe take a taſte thereof, in reading a Chapter betwixt euery nappe, and ſo happily
<pb facs="tcp:25534:5"/>may be thereby incouraged to proceede with the reſt as appetite and good deſire ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe vpon them.</p>
            <p>Moſt humbly praying the holy ſpirit of God, who firſt mooued Saint <hi>Peter</hi> to giue this watchword, and inſpired and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed my minde thus to explaine it, and to publiſh the ſame for the good I truſt of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; to bleſſe this little labour of mine, and to make it fruitfull, with the dew of his grace, as well in the heart of the ſower, as in the minds of thoſe that ſhall reape any profit thereby. And ſo gentle Reader I wiſh thee well to fare, as thy ſoule fareth: and in thy prayers I pray thee, remember him that prayeth dayly for thee, and for all them that looke for the appearing of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, to their immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. Veni citò do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Ieſu.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25534:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:25534:6"/>
            <head>SAINT PETERS Watch-word.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>The end of all things is at hand.
<bibl>
                     <hi>1. Pet. 4.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>The firſt Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He almightie Creator, being without begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or ending, <hi>Alpha,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 1.2</note> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the firſt and the laſt, hath made this world for a time, and appoynted an ende thereunto to cut off all time.</p>
               <p>Man <hi>Microcoſmos,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man the beautie of the world is to be ſeen.</note> who contayneth as alſo the Philoſophers could ſay, a ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the whole world in a verie little continent or body, is firſt an infant, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a child, then a young man, after that
<pb facs="tcp:25534:7"/>comes middle age, a ſhorte time more, then doting old age, then (<hi>finis diſſolutionis properans</hi>) looke for the ending of this life.</p>
               <p>The world likewiſe hath had an infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie from the beginning to <hi>Noahs floud,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The ages of the world.</note> then childhoode from <hi>Noahs floud</hi> to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> then youthful age, from <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Dauid,</hi> then middle age vnto the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie of <hi>Babylon,</hi> a ſhort time more, then came our Sauiour Chriſt in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of olde age, which is alſo called the laſt age: then high time to conſider of the ending or diſſoluing of all mortall things. For how great folly ſhould it be in any mortall man (though neuer ſo ſtrong by conſtitution of nature) hauing once paſſed ouer, not only his yong and youthfull age, but his middle and ſtrong age, and entred into olde age, if then he ſhould not be mindfull of his ende, how faſt it ſtealeth on?</p>
               <p>VVhat maruell then, that <hi>Saint Peter</hi> knowing ſo many ages of the world paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and the laſt age of the world wel en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in if in a due co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration thereof he breake out into this moſt Chriſtian-like exclamation or forewarning, which may very well be called his Watchword, <hi>Finis
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:25534:7"/>omnium imminet: The ende of all thinges is at hande.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> who liued but in the beginning or entrie of this laſt age, were ſo carefull and regardfull to giue this Watchworde or fore warning of ſome great daunger enſuing, how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and regardfull ought we to be, that liue as it were in the laſt poynt of this laſt age, ſo to receiue and conſider of the ſame forewarning,
<note place="margin">A good Meditation</note> as may be moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the ſpirit of God, and moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for the health of our ſoules?</p>
               <p>For this cauſe onely was I incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, to vndertake this little labour at times of leyſure, and to leaue this <hi>Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word</hi> with the Centinell of our Engliſh campe, that euery Chriſtian ſouldier hereby may be warned to keepe himſelf within the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe of his gard or watch, and that at no time he bee found either idle, ſleepie, or ill occupied.</p>
               <p>And that this thing may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter effected, the Watchword it ſelfe, <hi>The end of all things is at hand,</hi> ought throughly to be weighed and conſidered.</p>
               <p>Our Engliſh tranſlations ſayth,
<note place="margin">The weight of S. Peters wordes.</note> 
                  <hi>Now the end of all things is at hand:</hi> euery worde carrying his waight: <hi>Now the end is at hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:8"/>The Apoſtle doth not forewarne, of danger long after to be looked for, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dooth hee giue warning that the world ſhall haue an ende one thouſande or two thouſande yeares after:
<note place="margin">The mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Apoſtles wordes.</note> but ſpeaking in the preſentence ſaith, <hi>Nowe the ende is at hand:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay: now it is time for euery one to waite for the comming of his Maiſter, nowe it is high time for euery one to haue a care of his buſineſſe, and to make vp his reckoning and account perfect. <hi>The end of all things:</hi> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> doth not ſay the end of ſome thing, or the end of many things, nor the end of moſt things, but <hi>the end of althings,</hi> the end of all things (that are finite, &amp; to be deſtroyed) is at hand. So then there is a double doctrine to bee drawne out of the verie bowels of the Text.
<note place="margin">A double doctrine.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, that there is no time of ſecuritie left vnto vs Chriſtians in this world.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that there is nothing in this world that can ſecure vs.</p>
               <p>For the firſt,
<note place="margin">Gen. 6.3.</note> though the old world had <hi>one hundred and twentie yeares</hi> warning, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the floud came vpon them: though the <hi>Cananites</hi> and <hi>Ammonites,</hi> ſpent many hundred yeares in wickedneſſe before their ſinne was at the full: Though the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:25534:8"/>Niniuites had fortie dayes giuen them for repentance,
<note place="margin">Ionah. 3.4</note> yet fithence the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Chriſt in the fleſh, it is not read, that euer there was any yeare, or day,
<note place="margin">No time gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to liue ſecurely in, in this world. Math. 4.17 Cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.10. Chriſt and his Apoſtles preachers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> repentance. Rom 13.12</note> or hour or minute, giuen to any man, to liue ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure in, or to deferre his repentance.</p>
               <p>Chriſt himſelfe ſaith: <hi>Repent, for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God is at hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> his foretunner ſaith, <hi>Repent, for the axe is laid to the roote of the tree.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> the Doctor of the Gentiles, he noteth vnto vs the reaſon of the time ſaying: <hi>It is now time, that wee ſhoulde ariſe from the ſleepe of ſinne: The night is paſt, the day is now come, let vs caſt away the workes of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore is it that ſaint <hi>Peter</hi> is bold to ſay, <hi>Now the end is at hand,</hi> it is high time to bee ſober and watching in prayer.</p>
               <p>Neither doth ſaint <hi>Peter</hi> onely vrge this argument to keepe vs from ſecurity, but ſaint <hi>Paul</hi> likewiſe vrgeth the ſame when he ſayth to the Corinthians,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Theſe things are written for example vnto vs, vpon whom the endes of the world are come.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam 3.8.</note> And ſaint <hi>Iames</hi> ſayth, <hi>The comming of the Lorde draweth neare.</hi> And the Iudge himſelfe, <hi>Beholde I come ſhortly,
<note place="margin">Reu. 22.7.20.</note> And ſurely I come quickly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:9"/>Out alacke then vpon the ſecuritie of our dayes,
<note place="margin">Duines in heauenly things.</note> and the dulnes of our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in heauenly things! we are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie pregnant to do euill, but to doe well we haue no knowledge: we are very skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to diſtinguiſh the ſeaſons of the yeare, but haue no skil to know the time of our viſitation.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtles of Chriſt ſaid, and haue put their ſayings in writing long agone, that the comming of Chriſt is at hand. The Atheiſts neuer cried out faſter then at this day,
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.4. Reu. 21.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Where is the promiſe of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming?</hi> Chriſt himſelfe ſayth, <hi>Surely</hi> I <hi>come quickely,</hi> The vnrighteous Steward euery were ſayth,
<note place="margin">Mat. 24.48.</note> 
                  <hi>Surely my Maiſter will deferre his comming.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now whom muſt we belieue, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, or the Atheiſt: the falſe Steward, or Chriſt Ieſus the Authour of all truth?</p>
               <p>The Scripture hath alreadie decided this queſtion,
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.4.</note> when it ſayth, <hi>Let God bee true and euery man a lier:</hi> and if euery man be a lier, no maruaile that the Atheiſts and deceitfull Stewards of this worlde, deceyue themſelues with lies and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors.
<note place="margin">The error of the Atheiſt.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The error of the Atheiſt ſaint <hi>Peter</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:25534:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſetteth downe to be their ignoraunce in the knowledge of God, and his worde, meaſuring Gods eternitie, according to their owne capacitie: And ſo like vnto them that deceyue themſelues, thus they reaſon: It is long ſithence (ſay they) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred yeres gone, that ſome haue ſpoken and written of the ende of the world: and they that then ſpake or wrote of it, made ſhew as though it had beene euen at hande: but now wee plainly ſee there is no ſuch matter, they are meere deceiuers, that haue told vs theſe things. For euery thing continueth a little from the beginning of the creation, and ſince our fathers died, the Sunne, Moone, and planets in the Firmament, the trees and Plants in the field, men and beaſts vpon the earth, fiſhes in the water, foules fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the skies, the ſea ebbing &amp; flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, times and ſeaſons continuing, colde and heat, Summer and Winter, ſeedtime and harueſt, euerie thing as it was from the beginning of the creation, therefore we will ſet our hearts at reſt, we will take our pleaſures in this worlde,
<note place="margin">Preaching to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that periſh foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</note> we will not beleeue the babbling of preachers, that crie vpon vs ſtil of the end of the world, we will eate and drinke, and riſe vp to
<pb facs="tcp:25534:10"/>play, we wil quaffe, &amp; carrowſe luſtily, we wil drinke healths vntill we be ſicke,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aggering <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>earers.</note> we wil ſwagger &amp; ſweare by the eternall Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and will leaue no ſinne vmought for, no not the ſinne of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dome.</p>
               <p>But ſtay there thon ſwaggerer, by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as thou ſayeſt, and doing as thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, the propheſies both of <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>Paule</hi> are accompliſhed, and the godly more aſſured then euer before, that the end of all things is at hand.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paule</hi> he plainely painteth out theſe perſons, and pointeth out the time when they ſhould come,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Tim. 3.7.</note> ſaying: <hi>This know, that in the laſt daies,</hi> that is in the latter times of this laſt age, <hi>ſhall come perillous times, for men ſhall be louers of their own ſelues, couetous, boaſters, proude, curſed ſpeakers, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient to parents, vnthankefull, vnholy, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out naturall affection, truce-breakers, falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers,
<note place="margin">Theſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ers agree with our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>imes.</note> intemperat, fierce, no louers at al of them that are good, traytors, headie, high minded, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of pleaſures, more then louers of God, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a ſhew of godlineſſe, but haue denied the power thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Peter</hi> more preciſely noteth theſe Atheiſts of whom we ſpeake, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Pet. 3.3.</note> 
                  <hi>this firſt vnderſtand, that there ſhall come in the laſt dayes mockers, which will walke after
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25534:10"/>their lusts, and ſay, where is the promiſe of his comming? for ſinc the fathers died, all things continued alike from the beginning of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſeeing all theſe things fore-ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of both, by <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> are in our dayes moſt truly accompliſhed, wee may thereupon certainly conclude with ſaint <hi>Peter,</hi> that <hi>The end of al things is at hand.</hi> Yea verie neere at hand, and may therefore boldly ſay with ſaint <hi>Paule,</hi> the end, euen the laſt ende of the world, are come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs</p>
               <p>But before wee ende this poynt, wee muſt note the aunſwere of ſaint <hi>Peter</hi> to theſe Atheiſts,
<note place="margin">Saint Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> anſwere Atheiſts.</note> that meaſure the infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Gods eternitie, with their onely conceyt of time, which time if it bee any thing, it is the leaſt of all thinges with God.</p>
               <p>Therfore ſaint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith &amp; borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it out of the Pſalmiſt,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.</note> that <hi>one day with the Lord is as a thouſand yeares, and a thouſand yeares as one day,</hi> which is a full anſwere to this their queſtion, <hi>Where is the promiſe of his comming?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now doth God promiſe and not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme? God forbid.
<note place="margin">God alw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> as goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>But (ſay they) it was promiſed long ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence
<pb facs="tcp:25534:11"/>fifteene hundred yeares gone, that Chriſt would come verie ſhortly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to iudgement, and yet to this day hee is not come, nay to our ſeeming hee is as farre of now, as he was then: therefore it is moſt likely hee will not come at all. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> though he were no ſophiſter, preſently findeth out this fallacie, and ſhewes whence they deceiue themſelues: namely, becauſe they thinke that time paſſeth away as faſt with God, as it doth with man, which is nothing ſo, a thouſand yeares with man, is a long time, with God, but as one day: why then was it promiſed fifteene hundred yeares gone, that the worlde ſhould ſhortly haue an ende? All that time is with God but as one day, and ahalfe day: ſtay but one halfe day more, and thou ſhalt be ſure to ſee the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof.</p>
               <p>So then they which iudge or weigh Gods euerlaſting eternitie, in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of their temporall vanitie, ſhewe plainly that they know not what eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and euerlaſtingneſſe is,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ongtime <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aſured Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>itie is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y ſhor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> for in eternity there is neither length nor ſhortneſſe of time, with God there is no time paſt, neither any to come, all things are with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:25534:11"/>God in the preſent tenſe, or time, and in eternitie there is neither length nor ſhortnes of time. Only of this fond con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit that Gods euerlaſting prouidence, is ſubiect to caſualtie of time, hath ſpru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g theſe groſſe errors, and hath cauſed the curioſitie of man to moue theſe and ſuch like queſtions of vanitie,
<note place="margin">Curious queſtion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> as how co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth it to paſſe that God forbore ſo long time before hee made this worlde! what did God before hee made this worlde, and the like?</p>
               <p>To which latter queſtion one anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth verie pithely, that afore God made this worlde for man to liue in, hee made hell for ſuch curious queſtioniſts to dwel in, after this world is ended.</p>
               <p>Againe, they that demaund why God forbore ſo long time before hee made this world, might as wel aske why it plea ſed God to make this world or any time at all? And the terming of any time long, is in reſpect of the continuance of time, to them onely that liue in time, and not in reſpect of God that made time. Put the cauſe that the world had laſted one hundred thouſand yeares, or if yee will ten hundred thouſand yeares, what ſhall ye gaine by that: you will then ſay, that
<pb facs="tcp:25534:12"/>the world had beene of the greater anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, but I demaund in reſpect of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? of God, or of thy ſelfe? of eternitie, or of time? truly onely in reſpect of thy ſelfe, and of time, but not in reſpect of God, or of eternitie: one hundred thouſande thouſand yeares paſt with God is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and ten hundred thouſand thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years to come with God is nothing, in reſpect of eternitie or euerlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and theſe diſtinctions of time and place, were created and brought forth togither at one inſtant with the worlde, ſo as they be neither without it, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it:
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> thout <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e.</note> he that is without time, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out place, made both time and place, and if he had beene ſubiect to time &amp; place, (as thou Atheiſt imagineſt) he could not haue made either time or place. So then be fatisfied with this replie of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, a thouſand yeares with God is as one day, &amp; one day as a thouſand years: Neuer demaunde this queſtion more, Where is the promiſe of Chriſts co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming? <hi>for comming he will come,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>b. 10.37.</note> and will not tary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Aſſure thy ſelfe, the Lord is not ſlacke in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omming as thou counteſt ſlackenes, but tarrieth patiently yet a verye little while, &amp; expecteth thy repentance, take
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:25534:12"/>heede therfore that thou doe not <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the hardnes of thine heart which cannot repent, heape vnto thy ſelfe wrath,
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.5.</note> againſt this great day of wrath,</hi> and declaration of the iuſt iudgement of God.</p>
               <p>So much briefly touching the error of the open Atheiſt, and ſaint <hi>Peters</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply thereunto.</p>
               <p>Now the error of the ſecure or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous ſteward,
<note place="margin">The ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</note> though it bee very dangerous, yet it is not altogither ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious. One ſaith, that there ſhall be no iudgement, the other ſaith, <hi>My maſter will deferre his comming vnto iudgement,</hi> for ſo ſaith the vniuſt ſteward, Surely my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter wil deferre his comming, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he giueth himſelfe licence to ſinne, and to liue ſecurely in this world.</p>
               <p>So then the cauſe of ſo great ſecuritie as is now in the worlde, euen of ſuch as voluntarily confeſſe and acknowledge Ieſus Chriſt to bee their maiſter, euen in thoſe whome hee hath repoſed great truſt, and committed many talents vnto their credite and gouernance, yea many ſuch as hee hath made ruler ouer his wholehouſe, not only to keep good rule themſelues, but alſo to keep many other in good order. I ſay, the cauſe of all this ſecurity in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is noted in this one word,
<pb facs="tcp:25534:13"/>ſurely my Maſter will deferre his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming: againſt which ſinne of ſecuritie, our ſauiour himſelfe doth inueigh moſt ſharpely ſaying:
<note place="margin">Math. 24.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Who is a faithfull ſeruant, and wiſe, whom his Maiſter hath made ruler ouer his houſhold, to giue them meat in ſeaſon? Bleſſed is that ſeruant whom his maiſter when he commeth: ſhall find ſo doing, verily I ſay vnto you, he ſpall make him ruler ouer all his goodes. But if that euill ſeruaut, ſhall ſay in his heart, my maiſter doth deferre his comming, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſmite his fellowes, and to eat, and to drinke with the drunken: that ſeruants maſter will come in a day when he looketh not for him, and in an houre that hee is not ware of, and will cut him of, and giue him his portion with hypocrites, there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vpon theſe wordes then of our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, I may well conclude this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall affertion, that there is no ſecuritie in this world, and that they who other they be that liue ſecurely, liue moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly, &amp; without ſpeedie repentance, are like to be onertaken in their ſinnes, and hereafter to be puniſhed eternally.</p>
               <p>The ſecond generall obſeruation is, that as there is no time of ſecuritie in this world, by reaſon wee are to expect the end thereof euery day, ſo is there no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25534:13"/>in this world that can ſecure vs,
<note place="margin">No earthly thing that can ſecure vs.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe euery thing ſhal haue an end as the Apoſtle ſaith. <hi>The end of all things is at hand.</hi> No truſt then or confidence to bee ſet then in any worldly thing. <hi>Sampſons</hi> ſtrength, <hi>Croeſus</hi> riches, <hi>Solomons</hi> glorie, <hi>Abſolons</hi> beautie, all muſt vaniſh away, friendes though neuer ſo mightie, wiſe men though neuer ſo politique, valiant men though neuer ſo frolicke, cannot ſecure vs, no not a moment of time.</p>
               <p>Oh, that in time then we would learne to bee wiſe, and put no confidence in tranſitorie things!
<note place="margin">Ier. 9.23.24.</note> that we would folow the counſell of the Prophet <hi>Ieremie: Let not the wiſe man glorie in his wiſdome, nor the ſtrong man glorie in his strength, neither the rich man glorie in their riches, but let him that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth, glorie in this, that he vnderſtandeth and know me ſaith the Lord, for I am he that ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth mercie, iudgement and righteouſneſſe in the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence is it that ſaint <hi>Paule</hi> concludeth:
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.31.</note> 
                  <hi>Let him that glorieth glorie in the Lord: and he that putteth his truſt in the Lord, ſhall neuer bee confounded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore the Pſalmiſt truly ſayth,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.</note> 
                  <hi>It is better to truſt in the Lord, then to put any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in man: it is better to truſt in the Lord,
<pb facs="tcp:25534:14"/>then to put any confidence in Princes.
<note place="margin">He that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ruſteth in God hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge.</note> And, if the Lord be angry, yea but a little, bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the contrary, the ſcripture ſaith of the wicked that liue &amp; die in their ſins, or elſe ſhall liue wickedly till the day of iudgement come vpon them, that they ſhall ſay to the mountaines and rockes, <hi>Fall on vs,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 6.16.</note> and hide vs from the preſence of him that ſitteth on the throne, and from the wrath of the Lambe, for the great day of his wrath is come, and who can ſtand?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that this is the briefe concluſion of the ſecond obſeruation, that nothing in this life, or in this world, may or can ſecure or keepe vs from the daunger of that great day, of which ſaint <hi>Peter</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warneth vs, but onely our truſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in God, which the faithfull haue in him by the meanes of Chriſt. See then how much we are beholding to ſaint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> for giuing vs this Watchword, <hi>The ende of all things is at hand.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">No time of daliance in this world.</note> Whereby wee are taught that there is no time of daliance, nor any place left vs to bee ſecure in this world, alwayes we muſt watch and pray, becauſe wee know not what houre the ſonne of man will come,
<note place="margin">Math. 24.36.</note> as Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſayth: <hi>Of that day and houre knoweth no
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25534:14"/>man no not the Angels of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but as the dayes of Noah were, ſo likewiſe ſhall the comming of the ſonne of man bee: for as in the dayes before the floud, they did eate and drinke, marrie, and gaue in marriage vnto the dayes that Noah en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into thee Arke, and knew nothing vntill the floud came and tooke them all away: ſo ſhall alſo the comming of the ſonne of man be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Watch therfore,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>for yee know not what houre your maister will come. Of this bee ſure, if the good man of the cauſe knewe at what watch the theefe woulde come, he would ſurely watch,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> we mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> looke for him euery day. Luke. 21.34.</note> and not ſuffer his houſe to be digged through. Therefore be ye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo readie, for in the houre ye thinke not, will the ſonne of man come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the ſame cauſe is it that Chriſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs this great caueat: <hi>Take heede to your ſelues, leaſt at any time your hearts bee op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with ſurfetting and drunkenneſſe, and cares of this life, &amp; leaſt that day come vpon you at vnwares. For as a ſnare ſhall it come vpon all them that dwell on the face of the whole earth: watch therfore and pray continually, that ye may be counted worthy to eſcape all theſe things, that ſhall come to paſſe, and that ye may ſtand before the ſonne of man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But oh good God, how is this caueat of Chriſt forgotten in this age of ours?
<pb facs="tcp:25534:15"/>When the care of this life, and the deſire of gaine haue almoſt choaked all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, or rather when belly-cheere and drunkenneſſe, is more in vſe among vs that are named Chriſtians, then euer among thoſe heathen people, which onely ſerued their God <hi>Bacchus.</hi> O beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drunkards, what meane you to runne into this exceſſe riot of drunkenneſſe, without all mean or meaſure as now you do? endeuouring to excel the drunkards and toſſepots of all ages.</p>
               <p>In olde time it was ſaid, They that are drunken, are drunken in the night, for then they were aſhamed to be ſeene dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the day. But now it ſeemeth our drunkards are aſhamed of themſelues, if they be not drunken once with the leaſt euery day:
<note place="margin">Drunkards delight to make more drunkards.</note> nay they content not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with their owne drunkennes, but take great pleaſure and delight to make other drunke alſo, as is too apparant by their carrowſing and quaffing health to him, and health to her, and yet no health nor wealth to any of them preſent or abſent.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paule</hi> telleth thee howe thou ſhouldeſt vſe thy needye brother, though thine enemie: <hi>If he bee hungry</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:25534:15"/>(ſaith he) <hi>feede him, if he bee a thirſt,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.20.</note> giue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> drinke:</hi> but thou wilt make thy friend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rinke before he be thirſtie, and of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riend make him many time before hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>epart thy mortall foe: for how many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayes and fightings doe we ſee dayly to riſe of theſe vnhealthful quaffings? then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat belching of blaſphemies, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aturall murthers follow after, and in a worde, what ſinne is there that doth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccompanie drunkenneſſe? This ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull cuſtome of quaffing by meaſure, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ather aboue meaſure, was not allowed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the Court of that great king <hi>Ahaſhue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſh,</hi> no not in the time of his feaſting,
<note place="margin">Heſter. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> out rather a lawe by the kinges owne mouth made againſt it: would God ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aw or other were made to reſtraine this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o great licenciouſneſſe, or beaſtlineſſe,
<note place="margin">Vnlawfull drinking forbidden.</note> or hereby men are made worſe then beaſts: bring a horſe to water, and hee will drinke no more then pleaſeth him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or is ſufficient: but if a drunkarde once come where there is either Ale or Wine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e is neuer ſatisfied, nay hee will enforce others to doe as he doth, ſo long as ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her of them can ſtand in the place.</p>
               <p>It is reported that <hi>Diogines</hi> fel in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anie once with ſuch toſlepot compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:
<pb facs="tcp:25534:16"/>and when hee was quaffed vnto in wine, hee caſt it on the ground, ſaying, better one, then two, meaning the wine periſh alone, then he ſhould haue peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with it.</p>
               <p>Now let the Drunkards heare what iudgement the Prophet <hi>Habakkuk</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth againſt them, when he ſayth: <hi>Wo vnto thee that giuest thy neighbour drinke</hi> (meaning in the maner aforeſaide) <hi>and makeſt him drunken alſo,
<note place="margin">Habac. 2.15.16.</note> that thou mayſt ſee hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> priuities. Thou ſhalt bee filled with ſhame fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> glory, drinke thou alſo and be made naked, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cup of the Lords right hand ſhall be turned vnt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thee, and ſhamefull ſpuings ſhall bee for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> glorie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe.
<note place="margin">Pro. 23.29.</note> 
                  <hi>To whom is woe,</hi> (ſayth the Wife dome of God?) <hi>To whom is ſorrow? T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> whom is strife? To whom is murmuring? T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> whom are wounds without cauſe?
<note place="margin">The fruit of drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> Euen to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that tarry long at the wine and to them that ſee mixt wine:</hi> Therefore giueth withall thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> counſell: <hi>Looke not thou vpon the wine ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pleaſant it is: In the ende thereof it will bite like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Serpent, and hurt like a Cockatrice.</hi> Then ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the feate of drunkenneſſe, <hi>Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eyes ſhall looke vpon ſtraunge women, and thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> heart ſhall ſpeake lewd things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore it is not without grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:25534:16"/>cauſe that our Sauiour forewarning vs of the ende of the worlde counſelleth vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all things, to take heede of ſurfet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drunkenneſſe: and in another place noting the diſorders of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful ſeruant at his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſayeth,
<note place="margin">Math. 24.49.</note> 
                  <hi>That hee will eate and drinke with the drunken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For which cauſe I verily ſuppoſe that this vnmeaſurable drunkenneſſe of our age, is a manifeſt token that the ende of the world is at hand.</p>
               <p>And it is to be noted, that ſaint <hi>Peter</hi> taketh the occaſion of giuing this watch worde. <hi>The end of all things is at hand.</hi> Vpon this that he had ſaid,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>It is ſufficient that we haue spent the time paſt of our life after the lawes of the Gentiles, walking in wantonneſſe, luſtes, drunkenneſſe, in gluttonie, and drinkings,</hi> doubling as we ſee this worde drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: then by and by noteth, that if it ſeemeth ſtraunge to theſe wicked drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, and vngodly perſons, if any bee drawne by the preaching of the Goſpel, from running into the ſame exceſſe of riot with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But that the godly might not be diſcouraged, he ſayth, that theſe drunkards and vngodly perſons, ſhall one day giue account,
<note place="margin">Verſe 5.</note> 
                  <hi>to him that is readie
<pb facs="tcp:25534:17"/>to iudge quick and dead,</hi> of which iudge and iudgement we wil now God willing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede to ſpeeke of more particularly in the Chapters following, firſt prouing that there ſhall bee ſuch a day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a finall ende of all mortall things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſecond Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the confirmation of this point (being a chiefe Article of the Chriſtian faith) true Chriſtians, I know deferre the plaine and euident teſtimonies of Scripture, howſoeuer the Atheiſts &amp; Epicures deride all ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Let vs therefore begin our proofe with that ancient propheſie of holy <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">noch gaue teſtimonie of the end of the world.</note> who liued before the flond, and is reported of to haue pleaſed God, and therfore God tooke him away vnto him ſelfe, as it were in the midſt of his dayes, in reſpect of them that liued before and after him, when he had liued three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſixtie and fiue yeares.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Enoch</hi> the ſeuenth from <hi>Adam</hi> (ſayth ſaint <hi>Iude</hi> the Apoſtle) propheſied
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:25534:17"/>ſaying:
<note place="margin">Iude. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold the Lord commeth with thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of his Saints, to giue iudgement againſt all men, &amp; to rebuke all their vngodly among them, of all the wicked deedes which they haue vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly committed, and of all their cruell</hi> ſpeaking which wicked ſinners haue ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</p>
               <p>This plaine and euident teſtimonie of the day of iudgement, reuealed vnto ſo holy a Prophet and Patriarke as <hi>Henoch</hi> was, in the firſt age of the world, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the flood, God would not haue to be buried in forgetfulneſſe, though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other of <hi>Enochs</hi> propheſies (as it is thought) be loſt.
<note place="margin">Some of Enochs wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings loſt.</note> Therefore by his holy ſpirit, inſpired the minde of <hi>Iude</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, to record the ſame in holy writ, and the ſame hath beene taken and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted in the Church of God, for moſt authenticall and Canonicall Scripture, and ſhall ſo continue in credite among all the faithfull, vntill the ende of the world.</p>
               <p>Beſides, this ſame propheſie of <hi>Enoch,</hi> the Patriarch, is ſtrongly confirmed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs by the Prophets, Apoſtles, and by Chriſt himſelfe, ſo that no man maye doubt the certaintie thereof without great impietie.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:18"/>How fitly doth that ſaying of <hi>Salomon</hi> in the laſt of Eccleſiaſtes,
<note place="margin">Eccle. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.</note> agree with the former propheſies, as wel almoſt in word as in ſenſe? <hi>Heare the ende of all, feare God, and keepe his commaundements, which is the whole dutie of man, for God will bring euerie worke vnto iudgement, with euery ſecreate thing whether it be good or bad:</hi> that is, to the ende the good and godly may bee approued, and rewarded, the wicked and vngodly reproued and condemned.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paule</hi> the great Doctor of vs Gentiles,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10</note> vſeth almoſt the ſame wordes: ſaying:
<note place="margin">None ſhall eſcape Gods iudgement.</note> 
                  <hi>We muſt all appeare before the tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall or iudgement ſeate of Chriſt, that euery one may receyue the things that are done in this life, whether it be good or euill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in an other place, reprouing the haſtie and raſh iudgement of ſome, hee ſaith:
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Why doſt thou iudge thy brother?</hi> Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning raſhly, or before the time, <hi>or why doſt thou deſpiſe thy brother?</hi> Meaning in doing thinges that are indifferent, preſently he addeth: <hi>Wee ſhall all appeare ſhortly, before the iudgement ſeat of Chriſt where euerie one ſhall receiue a righteous iudge-ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And he alſo confirmeth his teſtimony out of the propheſie of <hi>Eſay,</hi> where it is written:
<note place="margin">Eſay. 45.23.</note> 
                  <hi>I liue, ſaith the Lord, and euery knee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25534:18"/>ſhall bow to me.</hi> Meaning when hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto iudgement, for nowe many knees bow vnto Baal, and many other Idols, and all tongues, euen the wicked ſhall confeſſe, that is ſhall acknowledge Gods righteous iudgements. And then the Apoſtle concludeth, that euery one of vs, ſhal giue accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of himſelf to God.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing the Apoſtle doth alledge this former teſtimonie of the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> to proue the iudgement to come, we may here adde another proofe out of the ſame Prophet, where it is ſayd:
<note place="margin">Eſay. 6</note> 
                  <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Lord will come with fire, and with Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots like a whirlewinde, that he may recompence his anger with wrath, and his indignation with flames of fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereunto agreeth that euident place of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> where purpoſely hee ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth &amp; entreateth at large of this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſaying: <hi>The day of the Lord will come as a Theefe in the night,
<note place="margin">2. Pet.</note> in the which day the heauens ſhall paſſe away with a noyſe, the element ſhall melt with heate, and the earth with the workes that are therein ſhall be burnt vp.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And a little before the ſame Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>The Lord knoweth how to deliuer the godly out of temptation, and to reſerue the vniuſt vnto the day of iudgement to be puniſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:19"/>The Prophet <hi>Ioel</hi> alſo ſpeaketh of this great and fearefull iudgement,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 31.</note> when hee ſaith: <hi>The Sunne ſhall be turned into darkenes, and the Moone into blood, before the great and terrible day of the Lord come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> likewiſe, as al the reſt of the Prophets doe,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 4.1.</note> which would be tedious to reherſe, ſpeaketh of this great and feareful day of the Lord. <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the day commeth that ſhall burne like an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and all the proude, and all that do wickedly ſhall be ſtubble: and that day that commeth ſhall burne them vp, ſaith the Lord of hoſtes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> euerie where maketh mention of this iudgement,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>The God of Gods euen the Lord hath ſpoken:</hi> Then he ſayth: <hi>Our God ſhall come, and ſhall not keepe ſilence, a fire ſhall deuoure before him, and a mightie tempeſt ſhall bee moued round about him, he ſhall call the heauen aboue, and the earth to iudge his people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, <hi>Say among the Nations the Lord raigneth, he ſhall iudge the people in righteouſnes, Let the heauens reioyce, and let the earth be glad before the Lord, for hee commeth to iudge the earth, he will iudge the world with righteouſnes, and the people with his truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And not onely haue the Patriarkes, Prophets, and Apoſtles remembred vnto
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:25534:19"/>vs this great and dreadfull day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but euen Chriſt Ieſus the iudge himſelf hath beene moſt carefull to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne vs of this day, knowing how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and retchleſſe the world would bee in this laſt and doting age of the worlde, inſomuch that when the Sunne of man commeth he ſhal ſcarce find faith on the earth, iniquitie ſhal be encreaſed, and the loue that ſhould bee betweene man and man waxing cold. In the foure &amp; twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth, and fiue and twentieth of <hi>Mathew,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; 25.</note> in the thirteenth of <hi>Marke,</hi> in the ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, and one and twentieth of <hi>Luke,</hi> and in diuers other places in the Goſpel, doe the euangeliſts record vnto vs the ſpeeches and admonitions which our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour vſeth touching his ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vnto iudgement, vnto which places for breuities ſake I referre the Readers for this time: the rather for that I ſhall haue occaſion hereafter to note the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt of them when I ſhal ſpeake of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of this iudgement, and of the prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration which the faithfull ought to make againſt that day.</p>
               <p>Theſe few teſtimonies alreadie alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged are abundant prooſe vnto the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and godly. And therefore I may here
<pb facs="tcp:25534:20"/>ſay vnto any one that ſhal read this chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> as a good writer ſaith, ſpeaking of the beginning of the worlde, and the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Si credis, ſatis tibi dictum eſt, ſi non credis, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil tibi ſatis faciet:</hi> If thou be a faithfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuer, there is inough ſpoken to ſatisfie thee, if thou be an Infidel, or an Atheiſt, nothing will ſatisfie or content thee: yet that the vngodlieſt Athieſt may bee the more inexcuſable, if hee ſhall happen to reade this Booke, it ſhall not grieue mee to adde ſome oher authorities and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons fitting this mater we haue in hand: not that any thing that can bee ſpoken can adde any weight to the proofes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie alledged out of the Scriptures: but only to fight with the wicked,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and to wound them as it were with their owne weapons, who euery where builde vp their fortreſſes of reaſon, and diſpiſe or neglect he word of God, which is able to throw down the ſtrongeſt holdes, and ought to bring into captiuitie all the thoughts and imaginations of man.</p>
               <p>Wherefore if the wandring thoughts of the wicked Athieſts wil not yeeld con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nt vnto this truth, what reaſon haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y to gain-ſay it? Surely none other but
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:25534:20"/>bare denials, and becauſe they woulde willingly not haue any iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, though their conſciences ſummon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment euery day, therefore they willingly cheeriſh and maintain this opinion, that there ſhall be none at all. And why mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell we at this, ſeeing they ſticke not to denie that there is a God, that the ſoule is immortall, that there ſhal be any reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from the dead, and therefore no iudgement to bee looked for; that the world had any beginning, and therefore ſhal neuer haue ending. This proceedeth wel inough, for indeed to denie one,
<note place="margin">One abſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie dra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> on anot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> is to denie all, as to grant one, is to graunt all: graunt the firſt, that their is no God, and all the reſt follow of neceſſitie.</p>
               <p>And why I beſeech you doe they not aſwell denie that there is a ſunne in the firmament, in beholding whereof they cannot if there mindes were not more then blindfolded, but beholde the glory of God?
<note place="margin">Pſal. 19</note> 
                  <hi>The heauens declare the glorie of God and the firmament, his handie worke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or why doe they not denie that man hath any ſoule at all, in which ſoule of man there is painted forth as it were in a table vnto vs, though couered with the vaile of ſinne, not onely an Image of the
<pb facs="tcp:25534:21"/>Godhead, but euen a liuely repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the glorious Trinitie.</p>
               <p>Againe, if the world had no beginning whence ſillie wormes as they are, had they their originals, who made them, or whereof were they made? will they ſay the world made them? Why they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are more excellent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the world: and the creature cannot be better then the Creator: will they ſay that they had an euerlaſting beginning with the world? why then doe they die, and returne to duſt? and ſo an end as they ſay, and yet wil by no meanes yeeld that the worlde ſhall haue an end.</p>
               <p>Thus when their wits haue wandered the world throughout, they ſhall bee brought into this ſtraite will they nill they, either to confeſſe that there is a God, and ſo the reſt to follow in order, or elſe they ſhall fall into ſo many abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, as the wit of man can deuiſe to aske them queſtions. For as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, I meane the learneder ſort of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will teach vs in other learnings a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall being denied, they are not to bee diſputed withall that deny the ſame, their reaſons will be ſo raw, and their concluſions ſo abſurd.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:25534:21"/>Againe, ſeeing <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> a Prince of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers as they call him, when he had read ſome of <hi>Moſes</hi> writings concerning the Creation of the world, could in his bording and ieſting maner ſay of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ille homo</hi> (meaning <hi>Moſes</hi>) <hi>multa dicit, &amp; nihil probat:</hi> hath ſet downe much, but how doth he prooue it?</p>
               <p>I ſay if they will needs craue proofe of God or of his Prophets, for confirming of truth; let it be demanded of them what proofe or reaſons they bring vs to maintaine their dotages, lyings, and falſehoods, what proofe or reaſon can they alleadge to make any one beleeue, or rather to be ſuch an Infidel to thinke, that there is no God, that the world had no beginning, that the ſoule is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall, that the world and all mortall things ſhall haue none end: if they will haue vs onely to credit them denying theſe things, without any proofe and contrary to all reaſon, why doe they not beleeue the truth, which is agreeable to all reaſon, and confirmed by plaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations, which as they themſelues ſay, is the ſoundeſt kinde of proofe! or why are they ſo partiall and iniurious to the Prophets and holy men of God, I
<pb facs="tcp:25534:22"/>might well ſay to God himſelfe, as once to doubt of thoſe thinges, which are plainely and compendiouſly, yea with ſuch harmony and conſent as is wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<note place="margin">The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of Scripture admirable,</note> recorded in the Scriptures? ſeeing they themſelues will thinke themſelues more then iniured, if we giue not credit to their writings, though many times they bee full of fables, and in knowen things different, and diſſenting the one from the other.</p>
               <p>But if they will not yeelde God his due in obeying the truth, let vs yeeld ſo much vnto them as to reprooue their falſehoodes, as well by reaſon as by wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker authorities then the word of God, which they had rather beleeue. In their owne reaſon, they both ſee and confeſſe, that many things in this world by the reaſon of the alteration of times, and corruptions of men, are in a ſort as it were ſhuffled together very confuſedly, the foole is exalted, the wiſe man deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the vertuous puniſhed, the vitious praiſed: what other thing ſhould this teach vs in common reaſon, but that there is a time to be expected when all this ſhall be redreſſed, all theſe corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions purged, and a perfection of all
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:25534:22"/>things reſtored againe.</p>
               <p>This much the Heathen themſelues haue confeſſed.
<note place="margin">The Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then held that there ſhould be a burning of al things.</note> That after a certaine time there ſhould be an vniuerſall burning of the world, which wee Chriſtians call Domeſday, and that immediately after, all things ſhal be ſet in there perfect ſtate againe, as they were at the firſt.</p>
               <p>Now among all the records of the heathen that intreat of the iudgement to come, thoſe ſayings of <hi>Sibilla Erithrea</hi> (for there were many <hi>Sibils</hi>) are of greateſt accompt among the learned, which ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings or oracles, as they are called, ſeeing they are extant in diuers bookes, both in their originall, and alſo tranſlated into our toung, I will not trouble the readers with them in this place.</p>
               <p>And as touching this generall Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment though it were neither recorded vnto vs in the ſacred Scriptures, nor by any other authorities or reaſons confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, yet ſurely Gods giuing of his Law,
<note place="margin">Gods gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the law a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie that there ſhall be a iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> not to theoutward but to the inner man, not to our deedes onely, but alſo to our thoughts, ſheweth ſufficiently without any other proofe that there is another Iudge, beſides the Iudges &amp; Maieſtrates of this world, to iudge vs and an other
<pb facs="tcp:25534:23"/>iudgement then their iudgement to be looked for, ſeeing there iudgement here proceede but to the outward deede, and by prooffes of witneſſes, therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in any wiſe pearce into the hart, to diſcerne what is within. For as it is the Soule that chiefely receaueth the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and chifely breaketh it: it is therefore the Soule that muſt come to examination, which cannot be done in this world. Againe, ſeeing the bodies are vſed as the inſtruments of the Soule, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to good or euill, therefore there muſt be a reſurrection that they may be againe ioyned to their Soules, to receiue ioy or puniſhment, at the generall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>But if theſe Atheiſts will mocke &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride, as well prophane, as diuine autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, which prooue vnto vs the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come, neither will yeelde vnto common reaſon, yet there is ſome thing within themſelues which they euer carry about to conuince them.</p>
               <p>I meane their own conſciences,
<note place="margin">Mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience tels him there ſhall be a adgement.</note> which ſhall euer witneſſe againſt them ſelues.</p>
               <p>For let them tell me, what meane theſe feares and trouble which terrifie them night and day, if there were not a Iudge
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:25534:23"/>and Iudgement to be feared?</p>
               <p>What made that prophane <hi>Caligula</hi> to tremble euen at the ſhaking of a leafe, but onely becauſe his conſcience tolde him of the Iudgement to come?</p>
               <p>When <hi>Paule</hi> preached vnto <hi>Felix</hi> of the Iudgement to come,
<note place="margin">Act. 24.26</note> then did <hi>Felix</hi> tremble and quake.</p>
               <p>And how ſhould not the ſinfull Soule of man be afraid of this fearefull iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſeeing the deuils themſelues are horribly confounded with the feare thereof,
<note place="margin">Iud, 6.</note> being kept in Chaynes vnto the iudgement of that great day? To draw to an end therefore, I am rather of this mind, then otherwiſe, namely, that there were neuer any ſo prophane or wicked in the world.</p>
               <p>Whatſoeuer they haue written or ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the contrary, (as the Atheiſts and Epicures in olde time, and our Epicuriall Atheiſts or Machiuilians in theſe latter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aies haue belched out many blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies againſt the truth in this matter) that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aue beene without this feeling in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences of the day of Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, only by the iuſt iudgement of God, that they might be the more hardned in their ſins, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey haue laboured with all their might,
<pb facs="tcp:25534:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:25534:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:25"/>rather to ſuppreſſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vtterly to quench the ſame, which ſting of conſcience, and fire of diſpleaſure, burning and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting their ſoules in this life, are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe indeede, but onely a taſte and beginning of thoſe endeleſſe torments, which their bodies and ſoules ſhal at the laſt day be adiudged to endure, in the life to come for euermore, in the bottome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pit of hell. <hi>Where their worme or ſting of conſcience ſhall neuer die, and the fier ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be quenched.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why then ſhould we ſpend more time or words, or yeeld any more reaſons or authorities prophane or diuine, to proue vnto them that there ſhall be a daie of Iudgement, and an ende of all mortall thinges! ſeeing they that would muſt gaine ſay it ſpeake not onely againſt all reaſon and authoritie, but euen in a ſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> againſt their owne knowledg and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</p>
               <p>As for the godly and faithfull, the confeſſe the ſame dayly in the Articles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> their faith. And if there be any other a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> no doubt there be ſome, that neithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with the <hi>Saduces</hi> deny the reſurrection <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the dead, nor with the Atheiſts den<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that there ſhall be a generall day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Iudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:25534:25"/>but onely ſtand in doubt, wane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in their minds, and maruailing how theſe things ſhall come to paſſe. Let them attend diligently, vnto theſe wordes of Chriſt, who ſaith thus vnto them,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.28.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile not at this for the day &amp; houre ſhal come, in the which all that are in their graues ſhall heare the voyce of the Sonne of God. And they ſhall come foorth that haue done good vnto the reſurrection of life, and they that haue done euill vnto the reſurrection of Iudgement or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo much for proofe that there ſhall be a generall Iudgement, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall an ende of all mortall miſeries.</p>
               <p>Now let vs proceede to the Chapter following, which ſheweth how this day of Iudgement is vſually called in the Scriptures, and what profit we may reap thereby.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>The third Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ouching that point, let vs firſt ſee how the day of Iudgement is noted vnto vs by Saint <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe, whoſe Watch-word hath cauſed vs to wade thus
<pb facs="tcp:25534:26"/>farre in this matter.</p>
               <p>In the third Chapter of his ſecond Epiſtle,
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.12. Stay of Iudgement called the day of God</note> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> calleth the day of Iudgement, the <hi>day of God,</hi> and though it may be ſaid that euery day is Gods day, becauſe he made all daies, yet the day of Iudgement more peculiarly then other daies, may rightly be called the day of God, and that for diuers cauſes: Firſt, for that God hath kept that day ſecret to himſelfe, and hath not reuealed the ſame either to men or Angels, no not to the Sonne of man as he is onely man, though he be head and Lord of Angels: next, it may be called the day of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe vpon that day the moſt mightie power and maieſtie of that great God <hi>Iehouah</hi> ſhall be made more manifeſt to the world then euer before, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding of the good, and puniſhing of the wicked.</p>
               <p>Then ſhall that ſaying of the Pſalm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt be proued true in the ſight of men and Angels.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 58.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Verily, there is a reward for the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, there is a God that Iudgeth the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer, it may well be called the day of God, for when God hath iudged the world by Ieſus Chriſt, then ſhal Chriſt Ieſus deliuer vp the kingdome to God
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:25534:26"/>his Father and God ſhal be all in all, then ſhall <hi>El Elohim Iehouah,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> deſcribeth him in the 50. Pſalme.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> 
                  <hi>The God of Gods, the euerlaſting God, God the Father, God the Sonne, and God the holy Ghoſt,</hi> be ſeene &amp; worſhipped of men &amp; Angels, in the excellencie of their glory, the ſight and knowledge of whoſe glory, ſhall be the full ioy and contentation of Gods elect, as it is ſaid in the ſixteene Pſalme,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 16. vl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>In Gods preſence is the fulneſſe of ioy, and at his right hand there are pleaſures for euermore,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now Saint <hi>Peter</hi> doth not onely call the day of Iudgement the day of God,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  <note place="margin">Day of Iudgement called the day of the Lord. 2. Pet 3.10</note> but in the ſame Chapter calleth it alſo the <hi>day of the Lord,</hi> meaning no doubt the Lord Ieſus, who ſhall iudge vs all. And Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh of the ſame matter, vſeth both wordes in the firſt Chapter of the ſecond Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 1.8.</note> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>The Lord Ieſus ſhall ſhew himſelfe from heauen in flaming fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in the ſecond of the Acts, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> reporteth the ſaying of the prophet <hi>Ioel,</hi> calling the day of Iudgement,
<note place="margin">Ioel. 2.23.</note> 
                  <hi>The great and notable day of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now he calleth that day the day of the Lord, becauſe vpon that day the Lord Chriſt, ſhall ſhew himſelfe to be <hi>Lord of
<pb facs="tcp:25534:27"/>Lords, and King of Kings,</hi> and he calleth it great and notable, both in reſpect of the great glory of the Iudge, as alſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the notable things that ſhal come to paſſe vpon that day, for then the Sun ſhall be darkened, the Moone ſhall looſe her light, and the Starres ſhall fall from heauen, yea, heauen it ſelfe ſhall paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with a noyce (as <hi>Peter</hi> alſo ſaith) the Elements ſhall melt with heate, and the earth with the works that are therin, ſhall be burnt vp. Then ſhall the ſound of the Trumpet be heard the worlde throughout, to waken them that are in their graues, Then ſhall all they that are dead, heare the voyce of the ſon of God.</p>
               <p>Then ſhall all the great Monarches and princes of the world, together with all their vaſſals, and ſubiects, appeare naked before the perſon of this great Iudge, then ſhall the deuils and all dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſpirits roare and cry, then ſhall all the wicked tremble and quake for feare, and ſhall ſay to the hils and mountaines, fall vpon vs, and hide vs from him that ſitteth on the throne, and from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lambe, for that great day of his wrath is come, and who may abide it? therefore rightly may this day be called,
<pb facs="tcp:25534:27"/>the great and notable day of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Moreouer,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <note place="margin">Day of Iudgemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> called a da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Acts 3.19.</note> the day of iudgement is called by Saint <hi>Peter</hi> in the third of the Actes, <hi>the day or time of cooling or refreſhing,</hi> becauſe vpon that day all the children that haue any way beene afflicted in this life, ſhall be comforted and refreſhed, eſpecially thoſe which haue beene ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with the heate of perſecution for Chriſt his ſake, they ſhall be cooled and aboue all meaſure cheared, comforted and refreſhed. <hi>They ſhall hunger no more,
<note place="margin">Reu. 7.16.17.</note> neither thirſt any more, neither ſhall the Sunne light on them, neither any more heate of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution or affliction, for the Lambe which is in the midſt of the Throne, ſhall gouerne them, and ſhall leade them vnto the liuely fountaines of waters, to coole and refreſh them, and God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo let vs ſee how Saint <hi>Paule</hi> noteth this day of iudgement vnto vs,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
                  <note place="margin">Day of iudgement called a day of wrath. Rom. 2.5.</note> in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> he firſt calleth it <hi>a day of wrath,</hi> as alſo it is called in the ſixth of the Reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the great day of wrath, bicauſe at that time al the enimies of God ſhal be ſure to drinke of the ſeuere cup of Gods wrath to their eternal deſtruction.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 11.6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>So ſaith <hi>Dauid vpon the wicked God ſhall raine ſnares, fire and brimſtone, ſtorme and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, this ſhall be their portion to drinke.</hi> Alſo in
<pb facs="tcp:25534:28"/>the ſame place the Apoſtle calleth the day of iudgement.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>dgement <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alled the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ealing. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om. 2.5.</note> 
                  <hi>The day of declaring or reuealing,</hi> both becauſe the iudgement ſhall be kept in ſo open a place in the viewe of heauen, earth, and hell, as alſo in reſpect, that then all ſecrets ſhall be diſcouered and diſcloſed, nothing is ſo hid, but it ſhal be made knowen, ſaith our Sauiour, alſo in the Epiſtle to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 4.13.</note> it is ſaid, <hi>There is no Creature, which is not manifeſt in his ſight, but all things are open and naked in his eyes with whom we haue to doe,</hi> that is in the eyes of Ieſus Chriſt, the Sonne of the eternall God, who ſhall iudge the ſecrets of all men by Ieſus Chriſt. Thirdly, the ſame Apoſtle not contented in that place to call the day of iudgement, the day of wrath, and the day of reueiling, but alſo he calleth it the day of <hi>the righteous Iudgement of God,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
                  <note place="margin">Day of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udgement <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alled the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ighteous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udgement of God. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 2.5.</note> why is there any day wherein God executeth vnrighteous iudgement? God forbide. For then how ſhould God Iudge the world, if there be any vnrighteouſnes in him as the Apoſtle vrgeth in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter following? And as <hi>Abraham</hi> pleadeth with God himſelfe vpon this point, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Shall not the Iudge of all the world doe right?</hi> that is, execute righteous Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:25534:28"/>at all times; why therefore doth the Apoſtle appoint one day among all other daies, for God to ſhew righteous iudgement, calling it the day of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous iudgement of God? Surely he doth it to ſome purpoſe, yea, for our inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, namely becauſe in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon courſe of the world, it is vſually ſeene and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, and many good men as <hi>Ieremie</hi> &amp; <hi>Dauid</hi> haue complayned of it, that the wicked are aduaunced, the godly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, the ſinner ſet aloft, the ſeruant of God abuſed, the meeke ones contrary (as it ſeemes) to many expreſſe texts of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, conſtrained to wander in wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, being deſtitute, tormented, and afflicted, the proud ones in the meane ſeaſon to inherite the earth,
<note place="margin">The god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> abaſed, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wicked ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>alted.</note> and to ſucke vp the fat of the Land; with a thouſand like aduerſities, that befall the godly in this life, whereas the godleſſe lye drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; drenched in all proſperitie; what thing I pray you at the firſt ſight, can there ſeeme to be more contrary to the iuſt, or as the learned terme it, to the Geometricall proportion of Gods righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous iudgement.</p>
               <p>To all which, although it might be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that there is a fallacie foulded vp
<pb facs="tcp:25534:29"/>many times in theſe words euill &amp; good, proſperitie &amp; aduerſitie, counting &amp; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling too, aduerſitie euill, when it may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be called good, &amp; proſperitie good, when it may be called euil: theſe you wil ſay be paradoxes, yet ſuch as Chriſtian Schollers ought to be acquainted with. Alſo that all theſe things do but deceiue the outward ſences of thoſe, that are troubled with thoſe griefes of the godly, and proſperitie of the wicked, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, that God doth this in the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe of his iuſtice, and in the depth of his wiſedome, both for the great good and comfort of the godly, euen in this life, as they themſelues doe many times feele and confeſſe, and alſo for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter downe fall of the wicked, as <hi>Dauid</hi> being well aduiſed of this matter, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth ſaying.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God ſetteth them in ſlipperie places,
<note place="margin">Pſal 72.18.</note> ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they are tumbled downe and periſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Although I ſay, this point may thus be anſwered, and that not amiſſe: yet Saint <hi>Paule</hi> doth anſwere the ſame more fully in one word, and doth decide this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, to the full contentation of the godly, and terror of the wicked, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king mention of this righteous iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:25534:29"/>of God, which is as much vnto me, as if he ſhould ſay, Be it that it ſeemeth by theſe ſundry euents, that dayly fal out in the world, both to the good and bad, that God is not iuſt, or to make the beſt of it to mans ſeeming, Gods iuſtice doth not ſhine foorth lightly inough vnto vs; Haue patience but a while, iudge of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing raſhly or before the time, a day is comming, and will not tarry, that thou wilt be of an other mind, when thou ſhalt ſee God to make a ſhort accompt vpon the earth in righteouſneſſe, and iudge the ſecrets of all men, according to true iuſtice by Ieſus Chriſt, according to my Goſpell or preaching, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Who will reward euery man according to his workes. That is, to them which by continuance in well doing (though they haue had many croſſes and lets) ſhall be glory and honor, and peace, and eternall life,</hi> to recompence them for the ſlanders, &amp; ſhames, diſhonors,
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and death it ſelfe, which they haue ſuffered for Chriſts ſake in this world. <hi>But to the wicked and contentious and to them that diſobey the truth of Christ his Goſpell, and obey vnrighteouſneſſe ſhall be indignation and wrath to recompence them at the full for their fury and diſpleaſure that they haue euer borne
<pb facs="tcp:25534:30"/>to Gods children in this world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer, vpon the ſoule of euery man that doth euill ſaith the Apoſtle, and hath not repented, ſhall be tribulation and anguiſh for a recompence of their vaine iolities and reioycings, which was their continual delight in this life, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with that anſwer of <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ke. 16.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Remember that thou in thy life time recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt pleaſure, and contrariwiſe, Lazarus paine, but now he is comforted, and thou art puniſhed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereunto ſerue theſe complaints of the damned noted in the booke of Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſedom.</note> we fooles ſay the damned, thought the lifes of the godly that gladly ſuffered affliction in this life for Godlineſſe ſake, madneſſe, and their ende to be without honour, but now they are counted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the children of God, &amp; their por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is among the Saints; contrariwiſe, ſay they to the increaſe of their griefe, we haue weried our ſelues in the waies of wickedneſſe &amp; deſtruction, and we haue paſſed through dangerous waies, but we haue not knowne the way of the Lord. Laſt of all the remembrance of their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in this world, doth moſt of all torment them, ſaying among themſelues, what hath the pride of this world profited vs,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:25534:30"/>or what profit hath the pompe of riches brought vs, all thoſe things are paſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way like a ſhadow? Then it followeth, for the hope of the vngodly is like the duſt that is blowen away with the winde, but the righteous ſhall liue for euer. And all this is according to the righteous iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Who ſhall Iudge the world in righteouſneſſe, and miniſter true iudgement vnto the people, as Dauid ſpeaketh in the 9. Pſalme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon then we conclude, that God euen in this world, in the vprightneſſe of his Iuſtice, doth deferre the Iudgement of the wicked at times, and alſo ſuffers many times the godly to be moſt vniuſtly Iudged and wronged, by the vngodly, for cauſes left knowne to his wiſedome; of whoſe wronges, he will ſurely be reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged either in this world, or in the world to come, or in both. Neither (as a godly Father hath well noted) doth God ceaſe to ſhew continually tokens of his Iuſtice euen in this life, leſt any ſhould thinke God were altogether vniuſt, and had no regard how matters paſſed in this world. On the contrary, he doth not puniſh all the vngodly ones of this world, at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for all their vngodlineſſe, for then he ſhould leaue nothing for the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:25534:31"/>to come. And withall it is to be noted, that euen thoſe Iudgements which God at any time doth execute vpon the godleſſe in this world, are but onely beginnings of their torments to come, to the which they ſhall eternally be Iudged at the laſt day, except they repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</p>
               <p>And ſo much for that Saint <hi>Paule</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the day of Iudgement a day of wrath a day of reuealing, and a day of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Iudgement of God.</p>
               <p>I will not indeuour further to enlarge this Chapter, by any curious ſearching of any other attributes or names, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by this day of Iudgement is noted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs in the Scriptures, whereof I know there are many other both in the olde and newe Teſtament: for as much as I ſeeke not a multitude of examples to fill the page, but onely fitte examples to confirme the godly, and to ſtrike a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror into the harts of the godleſſe for their good, if at leaſt any thing may terrifie them. Onely for the further com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the godly, who with great pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience muſt waite for the comming of their Maſter. Let it not be forgotten, that our Sauiour himſelfe in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, after he hath noted many fearefull
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:25534:31"/>ſignes that ſhall goe before and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie this great iudgement for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding of the wicked: he addeth a moſt comfortable exhortation to al the godly bidding them to lift vp their heads and reioyce,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/>
                  <note place="margin">The day of iudgement called a day of redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Luke. 21.28</note> for that <hi>the day of their redemption is at hand,</hi> for then and vpon that day, all the faithfull ſhall be ſure to receaue the effect of their former redemption, purchaſed by the death of Chriſt, and alſo the end of their faith, which is their eternall ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, both in ſoule and body in the life to come. This day thus noted vnto vs in the ſcriptures, hath been &amp; yet is vſually called of the godly, <hi>The day of doome,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then the laſt doome or definitiue ſentence ſhall be giuen vpon all fleſh, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to be reuoked.</p>
               <p>It is alſo called commonly the day of the ſecond comming of Chriſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>
                  <note place="margin">And the day of Chriſt his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</note> which ſhal be in infinite glory, to counteruaile his firſt comming in the fleſh in ſo great baſeneſſe and humilitie.</p>
               <p>Laſtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/>
                  <note place="margin">The day of iudgement called t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> laſt day.</note> it is rightly called by our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our three times in one Chapter. <hi>The laſt day,</hi> becauſe all daies and time it ſelfe ſhal end with it, for as time began when the world began, ſo with the world it muſt needes haue an end,</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:32"/>Therefore is it that the Angell ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſo ſolemnly in the <hi>Reuelation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 6.39.44.54.</note> (ſuch an other oath we ſhall hardly finde in all the Scriptures,)
<note place="margin">Ren. 10.5.6</note> 
                  <hi>By him that liueth for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, which created heauen &amp; the things which therein are, and the earth and the things that therein are, and the Sea and the thinges which therin are, that Time ſhal be no more,</hi> meaning after this world is ended.</p>
               <p>Now God of his great mercy there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore giue vs grace wiſely to conſider of the ſeaſons, and to make benefite of the time wherein we liue, and alſo to be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that this time or day will come how ſoone, he onely knoweth, that knoweth all things, though all the Epicures in the world, haue ſworne the contrary.</p>
               <p>The rather for that we are aſſured all of the ſignes fore propheſied in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to come to paſſe before that day are well neare accompliſhed and fulfilled, whereof we are to intreate in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:25534:32"/>
               <head>The fourth Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſignes and tokens that ſhall goe before this great and generall Iudgement are thus diuided by ſome.</p>
               <p>Into ſignes Phyſicall,</p>
               <p>In the heauens, earth, and Sea.</p>
               <p>Signes Politicall, in Countries and common-wealthes.</p>
               <p>Signes <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> in Church and Church-men, which deuiſion is good, and may well be followed, howbeit, my purpoſe is not at this time, to enter into any curious diſcourſe, but onely briefely and plainely to diſcouer and lay open ſuch ſignes and tokens as the Scripture doth forewarne vs of that ſhall come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this day, whereof many no doubt are paſt, and ſome may be yet to come, which we will alſo note as we ſpeake of them in perticular.</p>
               <p>And albeit I ſay there may be ſome fignes and tokens that are not yet fully accompliſhed,
<note place="margin">No man ought to defer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> let no man therefore defer his repentance, or thinke the day of iudgement to be the further off for that,
<pb facs="tcp:25534:33"/>for I ſuppoſe there be tokens that ſhal be ſeene to come before that day, no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then the lightning before the thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, betweene the which there will be no time for the obſtinate ſinners to repent, but euen for the faithfull and godly, <hi>To lift vp their heads and to reioyce, for that their redemption is ſo nigh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſignes and tokens that ſhall goe before this great and fearefull daie of Iudgement, hath Chriſt the Iudge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in token of his loue vnto vs deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed and made knowne, howbeit ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what darkely to the end the godly ſhould conſider thereof the more carefully, as the wicked do paſſe them ouer contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly, which ſignes we will briefely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite, as they are deliuered vs by Chriſt himſelfe, his faithful Euangeliſts &amp; Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.
<note place="margin">Luke. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Then ſhal be ſignes ſaith Saint Luke, in the ſunne, and in the Moone, &amp; in the ſtarres,</hi> which no doubt haue been accompliſhed &amp; ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, &amp; that in this laſt age of the world by moſt ſtrange &amp; extraordinary eclipſes of the Sun, &amp; of the Moone, &amp; by fearful &amp; vnwonted comets &amp; blaſing ſtars that haue appeared as wel to vs, as in diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places &amp; countries in Chriſtendom: all which do preach vnto vs, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of all things is at hand. And it is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:25534:33"/>vſually obſerued by the godly, that euen theſe heauenly bodies, the Sun, Moone, &amp; other of the planets &amp; ſtarres which by the God of nature were created for the comfort of man, haue of late yeeres with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held as it were their brighteſt beames, &amp; ſweeteſt influences fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, as bluſhing and hiding their faces fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beholding the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of this latter age wherein we liue: adde vnto this the alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which fal out in the times &amp; ſeaſons of the yeere: The ſpring ſome yeeres hoater then the ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, &amp; the ſommer more moyſter &amp; col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then part of the winter: yea, and the time of harueſt wherein fruits ſhould be ripened &amp; gathered for the ſuſtinance of man, hath ſhewed it ſelfe moſt vnkindly to requite as it were the vnkindnes &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefulnes of man towards his God, who gouerneth all theſe things accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his good pleaſure, &amp; appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</p>
               <p>The ſtarres &amp; planets are ordained as the clocke of God to giue warning to the world of that euent &amp; falling out of theſe inferior things,
<note place="margin">God the gouernor and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of all things.</note> but God himſelfe tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the wheeles, draweth vp, and letteth downe the poyſes as it pleaſeth him, &amp; cauſeth echthing to fal out according to his owne pleaſure. So that we neede not
<pb facs="tcp:25534:34"/>doubt to affirme that there haue beene many estraordinary ſignes in the Sunne, in the Moone, and in the Starres, paſſed already, and yet dayly are to be ſeene, to admoniſh vs that the ende of all things is at hand.</p>
               <p>Now, as theſe ſignes are vſually noted by the learned in the heauens, ſo the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes of the ſame are warres, famines, and Peſtilence among men here on earth, which are alſo tokens foretold by three Euangeliſts, that ſhall fall out before the ende of the world. And albeit no age in the world hath beene free from theſe Iudgements of God for ſinne, yet no doubt theſe latter warres which haue beene rayſed by Antichriſt, and waged by Chriſtian Princes, within Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for the Goſpels ſake, doe euen as it were point out with the finger, that Chriſt himſelfe is comming to ſtint this ſtrife, and to ſtay the fury of Antichriſt the Pope, and all his adherents.</p>
               <p>The like is to be ſaid of all the feareful famines and Peſtilences that wee haue both ſeene and felt, and the Lord of grace onely knoweth what is it to come before the end of the world for our great vnthankfulneſſe, and abuſing of Gods
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:25534:34"/>bleſſing in the time of peace and plenty: for as ſinne doth abound, ſo the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſinne muſt alſo increaſe.</p>
               <p>And that ſinne and ſinners doe ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe &amp; abound, what doth it elſe prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticate, but that as Chriſt alſo forwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, the end of the world poſteth on. Alſo that <hi>fidelitas</hi> faithfulneſſe or faithfull dealing among men is <hi>nigro cigno ſimilis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Loue, or charitie cold as ice.</note> rare to be found, and loue or charitie waxen colde as the ice, euen in the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of the Goſpell, it teacheth vs plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that <hi>The end of all things is at hand:</hi> What ſhould we ſpeake of the moſt ſtrange &amp; vnna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urall birthes that dayly are to be ſeene euery where, which monſters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde all courſe of nature, doe plainely tell vs, that the God of nature is angry with man, for thoſe moſt monſtrous and vnnaturall ſins which are dayly commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: to ſpeake nothing of the ſtrange &amp; vnheard of fires, &amp; burnings, haile, thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings and lightnings, which are euen the Harbenge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> or forerunners, of that fearefull &amp; violent fire, which ſhal ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroy all the aduerſaries of God when his Sonne Chriſt ſhall come vnto iudgement.</p>
               <p>Alſo there ſhall be earth quakes though
<pb facs="tcp:25534:35"/>not in all, yet in diuers places, &amp; we haue lately ſeene and felt the ſame,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uke 21.</note> the Sea and waters ſhall ſwell and rore, and that for all theſe things mens harts ſhall faile them and be aſtoniſhed, which thing euen ſurely doth euen now beginne to come to paſſe and dayly ſhall increaſe towards the ende of the world, all theſe and many other ſignes and tokens we may affirme without any feare to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready paſſed and gone, and thereupon we may conclude as our Sauiour teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs by the budding of the Figge tree, that the Sonne of righteouſnes is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to appeare in the Heauens, and the euerlaſting ſummer for all the children of God is euen at hand,
<note place="margin">Signes paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> which ſhall be vnto them a time of ioy and refreſhing, but to the wicked and vngodly a day of horror and lamentation.</p>
               <p>So much briefely touching ſuch ſignes and tokens as are already paſſed, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto may bee added that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of <hi>the departing from the faith,
<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2 3</note> and the reuealing of Antichriſt that childe of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> which the light of the Goſpell in this age hath reuealed, &amp; made knowen to the world, and I truſt will dayly more and more reueile to all ſuch as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:25534:35"/>haue not receiued the marke of that beaſt, <hi>either in their right hand,
<note place="margin">Reu. 13.16.</note> or in their forehead.</hi> But here it may be ſaid, that the Scripture teacheth that the <hi>Sunne ſhall be darkned, the Moone turned into bloud,
<note place="margin">Math. 24.29.</note> and the Starres ſhall fall from Heauen, before this great and terrible day of the Lord come:</hi> and therefore ſome may ſay we neede not to doubt of the day of Iudgement before we ſee theſe great ſignes ſo to be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed and fulfilled.</p>
               <p>But ſtay, are we aſſured that theſe great and fearefull tokens haue not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in ſome place or other in this laſt age of the world: or if they haue not been litterally fulfilled, yet may they not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically be accompliſhed? which thing by the learned is alſo noted, and obſerued, comparing the darkning of the Sunne to the Eclipſing of the Goſpell, being Eclipſed and darkened vnder the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Antichriſt fiue hundred yeeres together, the Moone turned into bloud, to the great ſlaughters &amp; perſecutions of the Church &amp; children of God, whoſe bloud by the bloudy beaſt of <hi>Rome</hi> hath been ſhed &amp; ſpilt as waters in al quarters of Chriſtendome, the falling away of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great Maſters and Doctors which
<pb facs="tcp:25534:36"/>ſometimes ſhined in the Church but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter declining vnto Papiſme or Atheiſme, haue they likened to the falling of the Starres from Heauen.</p>
               <p>All theſe things no doubt in this ſence haue beene fulfilled; but that this is the meaning of our Sauiour, that his words ſhall be miſtically vnderſtood, I dare not affirme, but rather I doe verily beleeue, that the Sunne in the firmament ſhal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede be darkned, when the Sonne of righteouſneſſe ſhall appeare; that the Moone ſhall not then giue her light, and for how can ſhe, when the ſunne is dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, from who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe receiueth all hir light and brightneſſe, that the ſtarres ſhal then fall from heauen, and no maruell, ſeeing then the <hi>powers of Heauen ſhall be ſhaken,
<note place="margin">2 Pet 3.</note> the Heauens or firmament it ſelfe paſſing away with a noyce, and the elements melting with feruent heate:</hi> Therefore I am perſwaded that theſe tokens ſhall not be accompliſhed, till the ende of the world. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as I haue ſaid, let no man deferre his repentance till theſe ſignes be fulfilled, which are ſignes and tokens that ſhal ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the comming of the Iudge, no otherwiſe (as alſo I haue ſaid) then a flaſh of lightning before the thunder, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:25534:36"/>with the thunder (though the light be ſeene before the thunder be heard) yet both are ſaid to breake out of the cloude together; ſo aſſuredly as ſoone as theſe tokens are accompliſhed, the Sonne of man ſhal preſently appeare in the clouds with power and great glory.</p>
               <p>This thing is plainely reuealed vnto vs by two Euangeliſtes, <hi>Marke</hi> and <hi>Mathew,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 13.24.</note> who ſay, <hi>In thoſe daies, that is, at the end of the world, the ſunne ſhall waxe darke, the Moone ſhall not giue her light, the ſtarres of Heauen ſhall fall, the powers of heauen ſhall be ſhaken: And then ſhall they ſee the Sonne of man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the clouds with power and great glorie:</hi> No intermiſſion of time between the one and the other, ſcarce ſo much time, for the faithfull to lift vp their eyes vnto hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen &amp; to receiue ioy into their harts, for that their expected redeemer is come.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, that thoſe ſignes are not yet accompliſhed, it may be gathered out of <hi>Luke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 21.24.</note> who maketh mention of <hi>the time of the Gentiles to be fulfilled,</hi> before he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of the ſignes in the Sunne, Moone, and Starres, But we ſee the time of the Gentiles is not yet fulfilled, neither I hope ſhall be fulfilled, till the ende of the world, therefore theſe ſignes and tokens
<pb facs="tcp:25534:37"/>are not as yet accompliſhed.</p>
               <p>But ſome will yet ſay, that Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh of the reſtoring of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the generall Iudgement ſhall come. It is true indeede, Saint <hi>Paule</hi> in the 11. of the <hi>Romanes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11.</note> maketh mention of ſuch a ſecret, which curiouſly to intreat of, is from my purpoſe; onely this wee may note out of that place of the Apoſtle, that Saint <hi>Paule</hi> hauing an intent to tame the pride of the Gentiles, that they ſhould not boaſt or preferre themſelues before the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who were the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall branches, affirmeth in the three and twentieth verſe of the ſame Chapter, that the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſhall be graffed in againe. For ſaith he, <hi>God is able to graffe them in againe, if they continue not ſtill in vnbeleefe,</hi> which if, or exception of the Apoſtle, being well noted, will ſtay ſober minds from concluding a generall reſtoring of any publike eſtate of the <hi>Iewes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the comming of Chriſt vnto iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; For as much as Infidelitie is that great ſinne, which hitherunto hath ſtickt ſo faſt vnto that Nation. Howbeit, we doubt not many <hi>Iewes</hi> ſithence their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, God of his mercy hath called, and dayly doth call vnto repentance,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:25534:37"/>that <hi>ſo all Iſraell may be ſaued,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11.26.</note> as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, that as all thoſe that are Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralites indeede, and by faith in Chriſt, depend onely vpon the free election of God, as alſo muſt the Gentiles if they will be ſaued: But in the meane while, let it not hinder any to looke for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of our Sauiour, till the nations of the <hi>Iewes</hi> be wholy reſtored, ſeeing if that were the meaning of the Apoſtle, wee know not how ſoone God may bring the ſame to paſſe, for a iuſt iudgement vnto vs <hi>Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles,</hi> neither yet how long they may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in their vnbeleefe, euen to the laſt day, if God do not ſhew mercy vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>And as for that the Apoſtle alſo in the Goſpell, maketh mention of the time of the Gentiles to be fulfilled,
<note place="margin">Luke. 21</note> if the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof be, that for their great vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulnes, &amp; contempt of Gods grace, the Goſpell may be taken from them, as I hope it ſhall not before the ende of the world, (for then the time of the Gentiles muſt needs be fulfilled) I had rather me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate vpon this matter, then make any diſcourſe thereof at all, onely let theſe wordes of the Apoſtle in that place, euer ſound in our eares that are Gentiles. <hi>Be ye not high minded, but feare,
<note place="margin">Ro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> for if God ſpared not the naturall branches</hi> which were the <hi>Iewes
<pb facs="tcp:25534:38"/>take-heede,</hi> (which word euermore goeth before danger,) <hi>That he ſpare not thee, being a Gentile and a wilde Oliue tree.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as for deciding of theſe queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, either touching the publike reſtoring of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> or ſmall reiection of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> before the ende of the worlde, (both which queſtions I rather hold ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiuely) ſeeing they are ſomewhat diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable, let vs in a Chriſtian lobriety, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confeſſe our ignorance, then bewray curioſitie, waying well that diuine decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Apoſtle, wherewith he concludeth that diſcourſe.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rſe. 33.</note> O the deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the riches both of the wiſedome and knowledge of God, how vnſearcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble are his iudgements, and his waies paſt finding out?</p>
               <p>There are yet remayning two other poynts of like difficultie to ſome, to be briefely touched.</p>
               <p>The one, whether the Goſpell be yet preached throughout the world.</p>
               <p>The other, whether the kingdome of Antichriſt ſhal not in a ſort continue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the comming of Chriſt vnto Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Of the former, albeit I ſpeake of it in this place, yet I am rather of opinion,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:25534:38"/>that the publike preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, ſhould be reckoned in the number of thoſe tokens that are already paſſed, and that the Goſpell hath already beene publiſhed, yea ſithence the darkneſſe of Popery &amp; Mahomatiſme hath beene diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered throughout all Nations of the world, euen as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> affirmed it was euen in his time, and therefore now the end of the world to be looked for. If any will ſay, why then the ende ſhould come preſently? ſeeing Chriſt ſaith when the Goſpell ſhall be preached, then ſhall the end come.</p>
               <p>I anſwere, that the word then, muſt not onely be referred to that time when the Goſpell is preached, or ſhall be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, but alſo to that time when the breaching of the Goſpel hath fully effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed that for which it was preached and publiſhed:
<note place="margin">The word of God bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly ſeed.</note> for we know the preaching <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the Goſpell, is that heauenly ſeede which muſt be ſowen in the Gardens of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arthly mens harts, which ſeede muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aue a time to be ſowen, a time to grow, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d a time to ripen; aſſoone as this ſeede <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fully ripened, in the harts of Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ect, and the reprobate made inexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, for not receiuing or for not yeelding
<pb facs="tcp:25534:39"/>forth fruite accordingly: then preſently without delay will the harueſt come, and the ſickle ſhall be thruſt in to cut the Lords corne, to preſerue it for his owne Garner the kingdome of Heauen, when the weede &amp; euery vnprofitable branch, ſhall be burned in that fire, that neuer ſhall be quenched.</p>
               <p>Againe, we ſee the day muſt dawne, and the day ſtarre of the Goſpell muſt haue a time to appeare, before the Sonne of righteouſneſſe doe ariſe, yea the ſunne in the firmament hath a time to riſe, a time to run his courſe, and a time to ſet ſo the bright ſonne of the Goſpell began to riſe as ſoone as the Son of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was borne, he hath run his courſe and hath ſpred the bright beames of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heauenly light by his Apoſtles and faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full preachers in all corners of the world ſometimes here, and ſome times there which heat of the ſunne or Goſpel, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it hath ripened and brought foorth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> liuely fruits of faith, in the harts of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> children: &amp; hardned the wicked to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> greater condemnation: then ſhall th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſame ſunne of the Goſpell begin to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> when the true ſonne of righteouſnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> appeare in the heauens, with power a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:25534:39"/>great glory glory: ſo that it is not to be doubted, but the Goſpell hath beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready publiſhed, among all nations, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the preaching thereof, ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue I truſt vnto the end of the world. Now touching the other queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whither the kingdome of Antichriſt ſhall alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue vntill the end of the world, I know it is doubtfully diſputed of among many Diuines, ſome gathering out of the 18. of the <hi>Reuelation</hi> and other places, not onely that it ſhall haue a ſuddaine and grieuous fall, as no doubt it ſhall, but alſo are thereby lead to thinke, that new <hi>Rome</hi> which is ſpiritually called <hi>Babilon,</hi> (like as olde <hi>Rome</hi> alſo was) ſhal be vtterly raſed and ouerthrowne before the ende of ths world: whereat all the wicked great ones of the world, that hitherunto haue ſupported her, and reioyced in her brauery, ſhal lament and weepe: and alſo hereupon ſome haue mooued queſtions &amp; diſputed vpon, what Chriſtian Princes they are that are moſt likely by force of armes to giue this great and finall ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw to the kingdome of Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>All this is probably collected by ſome out of that place, &amp; others of the <hi>Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> where is mention made of the fall of
<pb facs="tcp:25534:40"/>
                  <hi>Babilon,</hi> now there is no doubt as I haue ſaid, by the fall of <hi>Babilon,</hi> is meant the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of Antichriſt, which hath his chiefe ſeate at <hi>Rome,</hi> for therein all the godly learned agree. I will onely alleadge the authority of Maſter <hi>Bullinger</hi> in his expoſition vpon that place of the 18. of the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> whoſe wordes are theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He purſueth ſaith he, (meaning the Author of the Reuelation) throughout all the eighteene Chapter the deſtruction of olde and newe Rome: alſo of Heathenniſme and Antichriſtianiſme, and that with a marueilous plentie and euidence of ſpeech, euen ſo that you would thinke you ſure, all things preſently accompliſhed. And he vſeth alſo (ſaith he) a moſt godly order. For firſt the Angell declareth the deſtruction of Rome, with moſt apt and fit words: Secondly, counſell is giuen to the godly, how to behaue themſelues in ſo great dangers: then is added the maner of the deſolation, that like as Rome hath greedily and cruelly ſpoyled and deſtroyed other Nations, euen ſo it ſhall befall vnto her: alſo after this, a lamentation is made, wherein the Princes and Marchants doe mourne for the ruine of Rome, where they alſo recite the riches and pleaſures. Finally, the Apoſtles and Prophets reioyce of the iuſt Iudgement of God. Againe,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:25534:40"/>(ſaith hee) the Angell of the Lord, caſteth a milſtone into the bottome of the Sea, that ſo the moſt certaine &amp; vnrecouerable and moſt weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie deſtruction of Rome might be ſignified, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto againe are annexed the cauſes of ſo greiuous euils and the ſame finiſhed with the praiſe and gratulation of all the heauenly dwellers, hitherto Maſter Bullinger.</hi> By this therefore it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth plainely enough, that by the fall and deſtruction of <hi>Babilon,</hi> is meant the fall &amp; deſtruction of <hi>Rome,</hi> together with the whole kingdome of Antichriſt. But when this finall fall and vtter deſtruction ſhall be, or by whom it ſhall be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, Maſter <hi>Bullinger</hi> neither many other godly and learned men doe deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, rather <hi>Bullinger</hi> as alſo many others are of opinion that Antichriſt and his kingdome ſhall in ſome decaying and ruinous ſort continue vnto the ende of the world, for ſo he oftentimes affirmeth in his booke vpon the reuelation.</p>
               <p>And in the end of his firſt ſermon that he maketh vpon the 18. Chapter he thus concludeth, Here now ſaith he, the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God for as much as ſhe is proud (meaning the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> which preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before he calleth the Lady of al realms and Churches) for as much ſaith he as
<pb facs="tcp:25534:41"/>ſhe is proud, vaine glorious, careleſſe, and wicked: in one day ſhal come her plagues, by which one day, as he noteth out of <hi>Aretas,</hi> is ſignified a ſudden deſtruction, and that ſhe ſhould then periſh when ſhe leaſt thought of it, and her plagues he ſaith, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> reciteth in order, death, mourning, famine, and fire. And Stories ſaith he teſtifie, that theſe things were by the <hi>Gotthes</hi> fulfilled accordingly in olde <hi>Rome,</hi> whereof (ſaith he) I haue ſpoken before. Therefore he addeth we doubt nothing at all but that new <hi>Rome</hi> alſo ſhall by men and Gods Angels (marke his ſpeech) be torne a ſunder and pluckt vp by the rootes: by men and Gods An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, now how well the expoſition of this godly man doth agree with that euident place of the Apoſtle in the ſecond of the ſecond to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> is not hard to be diſcerned, for no ſooner hath the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpoken of the reueiling of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, but preſently he maketh menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his deſtruction, for ſaith he, <hi>Then ſhall that wicked man</hi> meaning <hi>Antichriſt be reueiled whom the Lord ſhall conſume by the ſpirite of his mouth, and ſhall aboliſh at the brightneſſe of his comming.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By meanes of which place or contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:25534:41"/>to the meaning of this place, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe no man may determine, but that Antichriſt and his tottering kingdome may continue till the end of the world: no otherwiſe then a moſt ruinous and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed Caſtle which ſhall dayly be batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red downe with the power of Gods word, preached by men, but ſhall vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſubuerted and aboliſhed by the brightneſſe of Chriſts comming vnto Iudgement: by the power of his Angels, agreeable to that ſaying of <hi>Bullinger,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore noted, that newe <hi>Rome</hi> (meaning thereby the whole power and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Antichriſt) ſhall by men and Gods Angels, be torne a ſunder &amp; pluckt vp by the rootes.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I am alſo of opinion, that it is a ſafer way to perſwade the children of God to indure in all places with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the tyranny of Antichriſt, though it doe continue to the end of the world, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to cauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon vncertaine coniectures to expect the ending of his tyrannies and ouerthrow of his kingdome, before the King of kings ſhall come in his glory.</p>
               <p>And withall let vs not ceaſe to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh &amp; warne all Nations and people of the world to beware if they be farre of
<pb facs="tcp:25534:42"/>that they come not neare vnto his Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh <hi>Babilon,</hi> if they be neare or in her, that they fly far from her and that ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily that they defile not themſelues with the filthineſſe of that Romiſh beaſt, that they receiue not his marke in their right hand, or in their fore-heads: if they haue already beene marked, that they waſh it out c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eane againe by true repentance in the bloud of leſus Chriſt: in one word, that none be partakers of her ſinne, leaſt alſo they are partakers of her puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which in one day, that is, ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſpeedily ſhall come vpon her,
<note place="margin">Reu. 18.8.</note> 
                  <hi>For ſtrong is the the Lord God that ſhall Iudge her.</hi> And ſo much alſo for the deſtruction of Antichriſt &amp; his kingdome, which how ſoone it ſhall come he onely knoweth, which knoweth al things. And this I hope alſo may ſuffice to be ſpoken in this Chapter, touching certaine ſignes and tokens foretold in the Scripture to goe before the end of the world, whereof as I haue ſaid, many are paſſed and ſome of them may be yet to come. God make vs thankfull for theſe ſo gratious forewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and giue vs alſo grace wiſely to conſider of the ceaſons.</p>
               <p>And to the ende that nothing may be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:25534:42"/>omited as farre as my ſlender habilitie is able to reach, which may any way edifie or comfort the ſimpler ſort, let it be further obſerued in this place, that as it is on the one ſide too much curioſitie for any mortall man to determine or paint out the time or day of iudgement when it ſhall be, ſeeing it is not reuealed, but rather concealed by God him ſelfe for our good: ſo on the other ſide, it is too much ſenceleſnes &amp; want of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an diſcretion, nor to conſider ſo much of this day or time as may either bring pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite or comfort vnto vs. Yea, probable coniectures how long the world may endure to ſober and godly mindes I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe cannot be hurtfull, ſo that they be ſoberly auerred only as Chriſtian coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and not for any certaine or ſound concluſions.</p>
               <p>Such are theſe as godly &amp; ſober mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men haue not refuſed to ſpeake and write, as that it is probable the world ſhall not continue aboue ſixe thouſand yeares, agreeable to the ſixe daies of the Creation: and the ſeauenth to be the great &amp; glorious Saboath or day of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reſt, vnto all Gods children: and the rather is this coniecture receaued, for
<pb facs="tcp:25534:43"/>that the Scripture vſeth this phraſe or ſpeech, more then once: <hi>That one day with the Lord, is as a thouſand yeere, and a thouſand yeere as one day.</hi> And the prophefie of <hi>Elias</hi> which the <hi>Rabbens</hi> haue reported and thoſe of <hi>Sibile</hi> the prophetiſſe knowen to each ſcholler, do not a little confirme that coniecture; adde hereunto, that if times and ſeaſons be well compared to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, we ſhall finde, that from the beginning of the world vnto the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of <hi>Abraham,</hi> are neare about two thouſand yeares: from that time till the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> which came of <hi>Eber,</hi> a great Grandfather of <hi>Abraham,</hi> were ſubdued by the <hi>Romanes</hi> are alſo neare or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two thouſand yeares: ſithence that time the world hath continued almoſt one thouſand and ſixe hundred yeares: ſo to equall the yeeres of the <hi>Iewes</hi> with the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> there wanteth but a three or foure hundred yeares, which with God is but as a fewe houres, if with God a thouſand yeeres are but as one day, and who knoweth how ſoone theſe houres may runne out, ſeeing (as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny expound that place) <hi>For the elects ſake theſe daies ſhall be ſhortned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But among all coniectures,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> for I count
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:25534:43"/>them but coniectures, this pleaſeth me beſt and hath moſt often come into my minde, ſince God gaue me a minde to thinke ſereouſly on this day: namely, that this laſt age ſhall not exceede in number the yeeres of the firſt age of the world, now the firſt age of the world by Computation from the Creation to <hi>Noaths</hi> floud, were yeeres, one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, ſixe hundred, fiftie and ſixe, and the laſt age ſithence the comming of Chriſt in the fleſh (which is euery where called in the Scriptures the laſt age) is, as we all knowe and confeſſe paſt the yeeres one thouſand ſixe hundred: therefore I perſwade my ſelfe, Chriſt his comming vnto Iudgement is euen at hand. This coniecture alſo pleaſeth me the better, for that this ſpeech is ſo often vſed by our Sauiour himſelfe, when he putteth vs in minde of his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond comming.
<note place="margin">Luke. 17.26.</note> 
                  <hi>As it was ſaith he in the daies of Noath, ſo ſhall it be at the comming of the Sonne of man.</hi> And ſeeing now to our own experience, it falleth out ſo true in the manners of men in this laſt age of the world, as it did in the ending of
<pb facs="tcp:25534:44"/>the firſt age, why may it not alſo fall out as true in the accompliſhment of the times?</p>
               <p>How beit, (as I ſaid before) ſo ſay I ſtill, for as much as all theſe, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the like ſort, are but coniectures, and ought onely to be vſed and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not to hinder any ordinary procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in our callings, but onely to call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, that our Maſter is not onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, but that his comming is euen at hand. Let this therefore be a concluſion of this point, and likewiſe of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that the day of Iudgement whereof all this while we haue ſpoken, be not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to morrow, yet the time of our own death and ſo of our particular Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, may be before this day be ended. Therefore let euery one haue a care how he liueth, for looke in what caſe he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſo ſhall his iudgement be. <hi>Where the tree falleth, there it muſt lie.</hi> And ſo much touching the ſignes which ſhew vnto vs that Chriſt Ieſus is euen ready to come vnto iudgement, who onely himſelfe ſhal be the Iudge, whereof we are to intreate in the Chapter following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:25534:44"/>
               <head>The fift Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is an Article of our faith to beleeue that there ſhall be a general Iudgement following the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the dead, ſo it is not the leaſt point in that Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle to be wel noted and conſidered both for the comfort of the Godly, and terror of the wicked, who he is that is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be this ſupreame Iudge. The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle it ſelfe ſaith, <hi>He ſhall come againe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udge the quicke and the dead:</hi> that is, Ieſus Chriſt the onely Sonne of God and our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ord as wee confeſſe in the <hi>Creed.</hi> The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me Ieſus that was conceaued in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ombe of a Virgine, by the Almightie ower of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>The ſame Ieſus that was made Man for and dwelt among vs, he whom the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orld hated and perſecuted from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>adle to his graue; hee that was moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>acherouſly betrayed, moſt falſely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſed, and moſt vniuſtly by <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>demned to that moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:45"/>full death of the Croſſe: the ſame Ieſus Chriſt I ſay the Sonne of God and man, who then died for our ſinnes, roſe againe for our Iuſtification,
<note place="margin">Who ſhall be Iudge at the laſt day.</note> and aſcended into the higheſt heauens, ſhall moſt aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vndoubtedly come againe at the laſt day to iudge the quicke &amp; the dead; that is, all thoſe that haue dyed ſithence the beginning of the world, together with all thoſe that ſhall be liuing vpon the earth at the time of his comming.</p>
               <p>This Article is confirmed vnto vs by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>infinite places of Scriptures, whereof we may note a fewe for examples ſake. Firſt no ſooner was our Sauiour Chriſt aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or aſcended into heauen, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently the Angels of God proclaime hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deſcent or deſcending vnto Iudgement <hi>Saying,
<note place="margin">Acts. 1.11.</note> ye men of Galilee,</hi> ſpeaking vnto Chriſts Apoſtles and Diſciples. <hi>Why ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> ye gazing into heauen. This Ieſus which is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from you into heauen, ſhall ſo come, mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vnto Iudgement, as yee haue ſeene him goe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paule</hi> in the fourth Chapter the ſecond Epiſtle vnto <hi>Timothy</hi> plai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirmeth.
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.1.</note> 
                  <hi>That Ieſus Chriſt ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the quicke and the dead at his appearing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:25534:45"/>in his kingdome.</hi> And the ſame Apoſtle in the firſt of the ſecond to the <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 7.8.</note> that <hi>The Lord Ieſus ſhall ſhew himſelfe from Heauen with his mightie An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in flaming fier, rendring vengeance vnto them which doe not know God, and obey not the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Goſpell euery where menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is made of the comming of the ſon of man vnto Iudgement, as in the 24. and twentie fiue of <hi>Mathew,</hi> the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene of <hi>Marke,</hi> the ſeuenteene of <hi>Luke,</hi> againſt all which it may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected that Chriſt himſelfe ſaith:
<note place="margin">Obiect Ioh. 8.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>I came not to Iudge the world, and againe, I Iudge no man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the anſwere is eaſie,
<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> for Chriſt therein ſpeaketh of raſh, priuate, and partiall Iudgement; whereof hee accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the <hi>Iewes.</hi> In that manner Chriſt iudgeth no man, but ſpeaking elſewhere of this generall Iudgement.</p>
               <p>He ſaith plainely,
<note place="margin">Ioh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 23.</note> 
                  <hi>That the Father Iudgeth no man, but hath committed all Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnto the Sonne,</hi> yeelding a reaſon <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all men ſhould honour the Sonne as they honour the Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that none might thinke this
<pb facs="tcp:25534:46"/>Iudgement to appertaine vnto him one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as he was the Sonne of God, he addeth preſently in the ſame Chapter,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>That God hath giuen him power to execute Iudgement euen as he is the Sonne of man.</hi> Againe, it might be anſwered, that Chriſt ſaith, I Iudge no man, before he was glorified when he came to be iudged, and not to Iudge: but after his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly telleth vs,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tth. 28.</note> that <hi>All power in heauen and in earth is giuen vnto him:</hi> Wherefore Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith, in the ſecond to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> that <hi>God ſhall Iudge the ſecrets of all men but by Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n. 2.16.</note> And elſewhere the Apoſtle ſaith, when after Iudgement Chriſt hath brought all <hi>things in ſubiection vnder his feete then he ſhall deliuer vp the kingdome to God the Father.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or. 15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But it may be againe obiected that the ſame Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct.</note> That the Saints <hi>ſhall iudge the world and the Angels,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r. 6.</note> that is, the wicked men of this world and euill Angels, called Diuels. And Chriſt ſaith his Apoſtles ſhal ſit <hi>vpon twelue ſeates Iudging the twelue Tribes of Iſraell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereunto it may be anſwered that at the generall day of iudgment,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſ.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt ſhall ſit vpon the throne of his glory, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companyed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:25534:46"/>with his holy Angels, and all the elect by his Angels gathered vnto him, then as well Saints, as holy Angels, ſhall Iudge, that is ſubſcribe, and giue conſent vnto Chriſt his moſt righteous Iudgement; which then hee ſhall moſt iuſtly pronounce, againſt all the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate both of men and Angels: whereat all the Saints &amp; elect Angels ſhall great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly triumph and reioyce, no otherwiſe then it is ſaid in the <hi>Reuelation</hi> concerning the Iudgement that ſhall fall vpon the whore of <hi>Babilon:
<note place="margin">Rom. 18.20.</note> Reioyce O heauen and ye holy Apoſtles and Prophets for God hath giuen iudgement vpon her:</hi> So at the laſt generall Iudgement the holy Saints and Angels ſhall ſing the ſong of <hi>Moyſes</hi> the ſeruant of God,
<note place="margin">Reu. 15.3</note> and the ſong of the Lambe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Great and maruellous are thy works Lord God Almightie, iuſt and true are thy waies and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udgements King of Saints.</hi> So here we may. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onclude according to the truth of Gods word euery where reuealed in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utes: and agreeable with the Catholike <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rofeſſion of the Church of God in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ges: that Ieſus Chriſt as he is both God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd man, ſhall ſtand as holy <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Iob. 19.25.</note> 
                  <hi>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt vpon the earth,</hi> and come to giue true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dgement at the laſt day.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:47"/>The vſe of which doctrine is two fold namely, a comfort to the godly, and a terror to the wicked: for what thing can bring more ioy and comfort to the harts of all godly and faithfull Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſpecially to thoſe that are afflicted in this life, either in Soule, or body, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in both for Chriſt his ſake, then t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heare and aſſuredly to be perſwaded that Chriſt Ieſus their Sauiour an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> brother, ſhall come to be their Iudge That is, to pronounce them blameleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> through his owne obedience and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe in the ſight of God his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and to crowne them with eternal glory, and not onely thoſe as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtle teacheth, that ſuffer perſecution a the Apoſtle did, but all the faithf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> whatſoeuer <hi>that loue his appearing.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Be therefore of good comfort dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſtian whoſoeuer thou art, that gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt vnder the burthen of thy ſinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> feare not that dredfull Iudgement, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> if thou haſt faith in Chriſt, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truely repent, then thou mayeſt aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thy ſelfe to be one of Gods elect. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo apply that ſweete ſentence of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Apoſtle vnto thy Soule, which ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:25534:47"/>
                  <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect? it is God that iuſtifieth,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.33 34.</note> who ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne? it is Chriſt which is dead, yea, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is riſen againe, which ſitteth at the right hand of God, to make interceſſion for thee,</hi> which alſo it may be added for thy further comfort, <hi>ſhall come againe at the laſt day</hi> to giue ſentence on thy ſide, and to receaue thee vnto himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Contrariwiſe, Let the wicked Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, and all the vngodly ones of this world; which either knowe not God, or obey not the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, ſhake, and quake for feare: for euen he whom they deadly hate, whoſe word they beleeue not, whoſe Miniſters they regard not, yea, euen he whoſe bloud they trampled vnder their feete.</p>
               <p>He that was crucified vpon the croſſe, and had his hart bloud launced out with a Speare, ſhall in his owne perſon come to be their Iudge, according to that of the Apoſtle <hi>Iude.
<note place="margin">Iude. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> And Enoch alſo the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth from Adam, propheſied of ſuch, Behold, the Lord commeth with thouſands of his Saints to giue Iudgement againſt all men, &amp;c,
<note place="margin">Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> And eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eye ſhall ſee him euen they that pearced him through and all kindreds and people though neuer
<pb facs="tcp:25534:48"/>ſo pompious and glorious that haue not repented or beleeued in him ſhall waile before him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Reu. 1.7.</note> And in the bitterneſſe of their griefe and in the anguiſh of their ſoules forhorror and feare of that Iudge ſhall ſay to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; 5.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Fall vpon vs and hide vs from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lambe for that great day of wrath is come and who may abide it,</hi> And ſo much briefely concerning the perſon of the Iudge, now let vs conſider the glorious maner of his comming vnto Iudgement which is to be deſcribed in the Chapter following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſixt Chapter</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the fiue &amp; twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth of <hi>Mathew</hi> our Sauiour him ſelfe doth moſt gallantly and gloriouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe and ſet forth that his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to iudgement when he ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 25.2.</note> 
                  <hi>When the Sonne of man commeth in his glory, and all the holy Angels with him: then ſhall he ſit vpon the throne of his glorie, and all nations ſhall be gathered before him, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now our Sauiour Chriſt doth purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:25534:48"/>ſpeake of this his moſt maieſticall and glorious comming vnto iudgement, to counteruaile his firſt comming in the fleſh in ſo great baſeneſſe and humilitie. The which moſt admirable &amp; ſurpaſſing glory of Chriſt when he ſhall come, to ſhew himſelfe in the greatnes of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, we may not imagine, can be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by any reaſon or vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of man: for if as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith, <hi>No eye hath ſeene, no eare hath heard,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.9.</note> neither can enter into the hart of man to conceaue, the ioy and glory, which is prepared for vs in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: which are but the members of Chriſt.</hi> How great glory muſt that be which is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the head, who is himſelfe Prince of glory, yea and glorified with the ſame glory in reſpect as he is man, and our mediator, wherewith he was glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Father, in reſpect that he was the Sonne of God, before the worlde was: for ſo prayeth he in the 17. of <hi>Iohn, Father, glorifie me with the ſame glory,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.5.</note> which I had with thee before the world was.</hi> And whatſoeuer, he asked of his Father, that did he receiue as he ſaith in the <hi>11.</hi> of <hi>Iohn, That God heareth him,</hi> praying that is,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.124.</note> granteth his requeſt <hi>at all times.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore it is, that Saint <hi>Paule</hi> boldly
<pb facs="tcp:25534:49"/>affirmeth in the ſecond to the <hi>Colloſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 2 9.</note> that <hi>in Chriſt Ieſus</hi> (as hee is man) <hi>dwelleth all the fulneſſe of the God-head bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, or eſſentially.</hi> And in the firſt to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> the ſame Apoſtle alſo ſaith, <hi>That God raiſed vp Chriſt from the dead,
<note place="margin">Eph. 1.20.</note> and ſet him at his right hand in the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly places, farre aboue all principalities, power, might and dominion, and euery name that is named, not in this world onely, but alſo in that which is to come. And hath made all things ſubiect vnder his feete. And aboue all hath appoynted him to be the head to the Church, which is his body, euen the fulneſſe of him that filleth all in all things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if any would demaund whether the faithfull ſhall not be made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of this glory of Chriſt, I anſwere, no doubt they ſhall, for ſo Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſaith in the 17. of <hi>Iohn, The glory that thou O Father gaueſt me,
<note place="margin">Ioh 17.22.</note> I haue giuen them:</hi> that is, thoſe that haue or ſhall hereafter beleeue in his name. But here we muſt note, that there is a great difference betweene Chriſt the head and giuer of this glory, and his Saints and members which are made partakers of his glory, let vs a little illuſtrate this by ſome fit ſimilitudes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:25534:49"/>The whole body of a King, we know is glorious and very magnificent, but yet there is a great difference betweene the glory of his head or face, and the glory of his feete.</p>
               <p>The grace and glory of Courtiers ſpecially thoſe that are neereſt in fauour with the Prince, is very glorious: yet when they are higheſt in fauor, not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to the Prince in glory. <hi>Morde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay</hi> when hee was moſt royally arayed with King <hi>Ahaſhuerus his owne apparrell ſet vpon the Kings owne horſe,
<note place="margin">Heſter. 6.9</note> the Crowne royall put vpon his head; and Proclamation made before him, this ſhall be done to the man whom the King will honour.</hi> Yet euery man did know that there was a great difference betweene <hi>Mordecay</hi> who was honored of the King, and the King who gaue the glory and honour vnto <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, that ſimilitude which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle vſeth to note the difference as I ſuppoſe of the Saints in glory, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>one glory to be of the Sunne,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.41.</note> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Moone, and another of the Sarres,</hi> May very liuely repreſent vnto vs the difference betwixt the glorie of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt the Sonne of righteouſneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:25534:50"/>and the glory of his Church and Saints, who receiue all the glory from Chriſt, euen as the Moone and Starres receiue their light of the Sunne. And as the ſun is yet neuertheleſſe light and bright in himſelfe, notwithſtanding he maketh ſo infinite number of ſtarres and planets to ſhine through his light and brightneſſe: ſo Ieſus Chriſt our ſauiour the ſonne of the eternall God, ſhall in a moſt heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and glorious maner, giue light and glory to all his ſaints &amp; children, though they be neuer ſo innumerable, yet ſhall not his glory thereby any thing be dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, neither ſhall any ſaint or Angell attaine vnto the perfection of his glorie.</p>
               <p>The which thing ſaint <hi>Auſten</hi> me thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth by a pretie inuention of words, in the tongue which he vſeth, doth very wel note vnto vs: for ſpeaking in a certaine place of the glory and ioy that the ſaints ſhall hereafter this haue in heauen: ſaith thus, <hi>Non omne gaudium intrabit in gaudentes, ſed omnes gaudentes intrabunt in gaudium:</hi> that is (as I take his meaning may be) the faints in heauen ſhall not be partakers of all the ioy and glory of their maſter in heauen: notwithſtanding all ſaints ſhal be ſure to enter into their Maſters ioy,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:25534:50"/>into heauen: there to receaue ſo much glory, as they are capable of, and as each meaſure can containe: euen as Chriſt ſaith, to the good and ſaithfull ſeruant: <hi>Enterthou into the ioy of thy Maſter.</hi> In a word,
<note place="margin">Matth. 25.23.</note> Chriſt himſelfe doth make this matter plaine inough vnto vs as it ſeemeth vnto me, in the 17. of <hi>Iohn</hi> and 24. verſe,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.</note> where he ſaith, <hi>Father I wil that they which thou haſt giuen me, be with me euen where I am,</hi> that they may behold my glory: that is, as I vnderſtand it, that they may be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with me, and it to haue their glorie ſtill increaſed, in beholding that incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible, and infinite glory, which I haue with thee, as I am man their Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and Redeemer, which neither Saint or Angell can attaine vnto.</p>
               <p>This moſt infinite endleſſe and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible glory, is the very ſame which our Sauiour meaneth, ſaying:
<note place="margin">Matth. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>When the Sonne of man ſhall come in his glory.</hi> Now to the ende, that we might the better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue and conſider of this vnſpeakable glory of Chriſt, he addeth preſently three circumſtances of very great importance.
<note place="margin">Three cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> The firſt is, that he will not come alone, but like a King of glory as he is wil come accompanied and attended on with
<pb facs="tcp:25534:51"/>all his holy Angels, none left behinde. Angels and Arkangels, Cherubins, and Seraphins, and all the whole hoaſt of heauen, ſhall giue their attendance vnto this King of glory. Secondly, he ſaith, that <hi>he ſhall ſit vpon the throne or ſeate of his glory,</hi> alluding vnto the magnificence of Kings and Iudges, who haue their feates and thrones of iudgement erected and ſet vpon high, that they may be ſeene and heard of many people.</p>
               <p>Therefore Chriſt Ieſus who is <hi>Rex Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum &amp; Iudicum Iudex:</hi> King of Kings, and Iudge of Iudges: his throne ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue in the cloudes, where euery eye ſhal ſee him both in heauen, earth, and hell. So ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn,
<note place="margin">Reu. 1 7.</note> Behold, he commeth with clouds, and euery eye ſhall ſee him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So our Sauiour himſelfe teacheth vs in the 21. of <hi>Luke,</hi> ſaying, <hi>When the powers of heauen ſhall be ſhaken then ſhal ye ſee the ſonne of man come in the cloudes with power and great glory.</hi> The like anſwere our Sauiour ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vnto the high Prieſt, who asked him whether he were Chriſt the ſonne of God, thou ſayeſt it, ſaith our Sauiour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and hereafter ſhall finde it to be true,
<note place="margin">Math. 26.64</note> when ye <hi>ſhall ſee the Sonne of man ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at the right hand of the power of God,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:25534:51"/>and come in the cloudes of the heauen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This glorious comming of Chriſt vnto Iudgement, was not obſcurely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed vnto the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> as hee himſelfe teſtifieth in the ſeuenth of his Propheſie ſaying,
<note place="margin">Dan. 7.10.</note> 
                  <hi>I beheld till the Thrones were ſet vp and the auncient of dayes did ſit whoſe garment was white as Snow, and the haire of his head like pure Wooll, his Throne was like the firie flame, and his wheeles as burning fire, A firie ſtreame iſſued, and came foorth before him; thouſand thouſandes meaning of Angels miniſtred vnto him, and ten thouſand (a Definit for an Infinit num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) thouſands, ſtood before him, the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ſet, and the Bookes opened.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third circumſtance that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour noteth, is, <hi>That all Nations ſhall be gathered before him.</hi> This circumſtance ſerueth alſo very greatly to ſet forth the might, maieſtie, and glory of the Iudge, in that he will haue the people of all Nations to come before him, Kings and Keyfers, high and lowe, rich and poore, men, women, and children: none ſhall be priuileged, all muſt appeare. So ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>We must all appeare before the tribunall ſeate of Chriſt:</hi> All people that
<pb facs="tcp:25534:52"/>then are liuing vpon the earth, as alſo all thoſe which haue dyed ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world: howſoeuer they haue died, or whereſoeuer they haue been bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried: as well they that haue beene eaten vp of beaſts, and burned vnto Aſhes: as they that haue been drowned in the Sea, and eaten vp with fiſhes: all without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, ſhall heare this voyce. <hi>Surgite mortui,</hi> ariſe ye dead and come to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>This thing is reuealed vnto Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> as he teſtifieth in the <hi>Reuelation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 12.</note> ſaying: <hi>I ſaw the dead both great and ſmall ſtand before God, and the bookes were opened, and another booke wasopened, which is the booke of life, and the dead were Iudged of thoſe things which were written in the bookes according to their workes. And the Sea gaue vp the dead which were in her, and death, and hell deliuered vp the dead which were in them, and they were Iudged eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man according to their workes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O God of glory, what a great and glorious Seſſions muſt this be, where all people ſhall be ſummoned and conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to appeare! yea the Diuels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſaith <hi>Iude, Are kept in chaines vnder darkeneſſe vnto this day.</hi> O how great muſt the glory be of ſuch a Iudge, that ſhall ſo
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:25534:52"/>come vnto Iudgement, attended on with ſo glorious a troupe of Angels? who connot be rauiſhed with the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſo glorious aſpect, and moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable ſight? namely, to ſee the Sonne of man to appeare in the cloudes in the glory of God his father: all the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ſeruing and attending on him: and all nations and people of the world brought before him.</p>
               <p>Truely, if it be a goodly ſight to ſee the ſunne riſe in the morning in his brightneſſe, <hi>Prepared as a Giant to runne his courſe,</hi> If it be not a little glorious to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Moone and gliſtring Starres in the euening, which ſight no doubt doth cauſe the godly oftentimes to giue glory vnto God according as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 19</note> 
                  <hi>The heauens declare the glory of God, and the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſheweth his handy worke?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How farre more glorious muſt it be, to ſee the Sonne of God to appeare in the brightneſſe of his glory, with the brightneſſe thereof the ſunne in the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament muſt needes be darkned. To ſee ſo many or more glorious Angels, then there be Starres in the heauens, euerie Angell ſhining brighter then the Sunne in his ſtrength: together with as many
<pb facs="tcp:25534:53"/>Saints, as haue beene faithfull ſoules in in this life with glorified bodies, ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as the ſtarres, according to that ſaying of <hi>Daniell. They that be wiſe,</hi> (that is, all the faithfull who are compared vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wiſe Virgins) ſhall <hi>then ſhine as the brightneſſe of the firmament,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 12.3.</note> and they that turne many to righteouſneſſe ſhall ſhine as the ſtarres for euer and euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo much touching the glorious comming of Chriſt vnto Iudgement, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſt himſelfe in theſe wordes: <hi>When the Sonne of man ſhall come in his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and all the holy Angels with him, then ſhall he ſit vpon the Throne of his glory, and all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall be gathered before him there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue Iudgement accordingly.</hi> Of the order and maner of which Iudgement we are now to intreat in the Chapter following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſeuenth Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His point touching the whole order of Chriſt his comming vnto Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is very copiouſly layed open vnto vs in the ſcripture, ſpecially our Sauiour himſelfe doth reueale the ſame
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:25534:53"/>at ſundry times in the Goſpell: we will begin with that deſcription that Chriſt maketh in the fiue and twenteth of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 25.32.</note> who preſently after he hath ſhewed the glory of his comming, proceedeth without any ſtop to the order and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his Iudgement, for hauing ſayed, <hi>That all Nations ſhall be gathered before him,</hi> He ſheweth what courſe or order he will obſerue in their iudgement.</p>
               <p>Namely, how he will firſt of all begin with diuiſion, God doth all things in meaſure, waight, and number: God is a God of order, and not of confuſion: when all are gathered before him, he will ſeparate one from the other.</p>
               <p>This is the laſt worke, that God will doe in this world, And it is worth the noting, how God maketh his works to agree together, The beginning and the ending, firſt, in the beginning, God made all things by his ſonne, in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding he will iudge all things by his ſon, for who can better iudge of all, then he that made all.</p>
               <p>In the beginning hee made light to ſhine out of darknes as the Apoſtle wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, in the end he will turne light in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to darkneſſe. <hi>The Sunne ſhall be darke, and
<pb facs="tcp:25534:54"/>the Moone ſhall not giue her light.</hi> In the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning he ſeperated light from darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>In the ende, he will alſo ſeperate the children of light, from the children of darkeneſſe: <hi>For what communion hath light with darkeneſſe.</hi> In the beginning he made all things good, in the ending he will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all things that are naught, ſeeing the euil and naughtineſſe that is in man, or in any other Creature, came not vnto it by creation but by corruption.</p>
               <p>Therefore Chriſt ſaith, he will ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and diuide one from the other: that is, the good from the badde: The good he compareth to ſheepe, for their gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe, patience, and meekeneſſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: the badde, he moſt fitly compareth vnto Goates,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ech. 34.</note> who are a more ſauage and filthy kinde of beaſtes, The metaphor ſeemeth to be borrowed from <hi>Ezechiell,</hi> who bringeth in the Goates puſhing and hurting of the ſheepe with their hornes and troubling of their waters.</p>
               <p>Theſe filthy puſhing Goates that all their life long, deſire and delight to harme and wrong the poore ſheepe of Chriſt: wil Chriſt himſelf that great ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neard finde out euery one of them at the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:25534:54"/>end of the world: nonne of them ſhall be hid from his ſight. And becauſe theſe poore ſheepe haue a very long time with great patience endured theſe foule and filthy Goates, to feede &amp; paſture among them in the outward face of the Church, to their extreame hurt and griefe: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt Ieſus their ſheepheard with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any delay, at his firſt comming to iudgement, will gather and draw out his faithfull flocke of ſheepe from that filthy heard of Goates, and to the ende theſe Goates ſhall ſee the care that Chriſt hath ouer them, he will place them in their ſight, at his right hand of heauenly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection: the Goates contrariwiſe, he will ſet at his left hand, to ſend them preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to endleſſe deſtruction.</p>
               <p>But here before we proceede any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we are to note by whom our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt will make this ſeparation, namely, by his holy Angels which came with him and attend on him with all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy obedience. Firſt, he will cauſe an Ark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angell to ſound out the trumpet of God, in ſo glorious and fearefull ſort, that it ſhall be heard the world throughout, not onely they that are liuing, but they that are dead in their graues, ſhall heare the
<pb facs="tcp:25534:55"/>ſound of that Trumpet: and all the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſpirits, and Diuels in hell, ſhal quake and tremble with the noyce thereof. Then when all the Nations of the world are ſummoned and warned by that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Trumpet, Chriſt ſhall ſend foorth his Angels to ſeparate the Sheepe from the Goates, the elect from the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.</p>
               <p>This thing our Sauiour Chriſt doth reueale vnto vs in the Goſpell, and ſaint <hi>Paul</hi> doth likewiſe report the ſame in one of his Epiſtles to the <hi>Theſſaloniant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt Chriſt ſaith in the 24. of <hi>Mathew,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 24.31.</note> that <hi>He will ſend his Angels with a great ſound of a Trumpet, and they ſhall gather together his elect from the foure windes and from the one end of the heauen vnto the other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame doth Saint <hi>Marke</hi> repeate in the 13. Chapter.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, our Sauiour Chriſt doth at another time make mention of this glorious ſeparation as Saint <hi>Mathew</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports it in the 13.
<note place="margin">Math. 13.</note> Chapter, for hauing in that place ſhewed by diuers parables that the children of God muſt not be offended to liue here, for a time in this world, accompanied and mingled with the godleſſe, as the good ſeed is with
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:25534:55"/>the cockle, the Wheate with the chaffe: they muſt growe together both for the greater iudgement of the one, and tryall of the other, vntill the harneſt which is the end of the world: at what time Chriſt will ſend forth his reapers which be the Angels, to gather the good ſeede, the pure wheate, that hath beene well thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with the flaile of affliction, and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowed from the chaffe with the Fan of Gods Iudgement in the Lords garner: but the chaffe and the cockle and the Darnell ſhall be burnt in fire that neuer ſhal be quenched then ſhall the Iuſt ſhine as the Sunne in the kingdome of God their Father.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe, our Sauiour reporteth this ſeparation in the ſame Chapter by a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable taken from Fiſhers, which when they haue brought all manner of fiſh to land gather the good into veſſels, but caſt the bad away.</p>
               <p>So ſaith our Sauiour ſhall it be at the end of the world, the Angels ſhall goe forth and ſeuer the bad from the Iuſt, and ſhall caſt the badde into a fornace of fire, there ſhall be wayling and gnaſhing of teeth.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paule</hi> likewiſe in the fourth
<pb facs="tcp:25534:56"/>Chapter, if the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lonians</hi> maketh a like deſcription of theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things. <hi>The Lord himſelfe</hi> ſaith he <hi>ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> deſcend from heauen with a ſhout, and with the voyce of an Arkangell, and with the Trumpet of God</hi> according to that which hath beene ſaid already.</p>
               <p>But the Apoſtle in that place like a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he doth in the firſt to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a ſecret or two more, and he ſaith, that he doth it by the word or comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the Lord.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, that at the generall reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection at the day of iudgement, when Chriſt ſhall appeare, then they that are dead in Chriſt, that is, all thoſe that haue died in the faith of Chriſt ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world, ſhall riſe firſt, that is, before the wicked, that did not die in the faith of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The ſecond ſecret or myſtery is, that thoſe of the faithfull, that are liuing at the day of iudgement of whom the ſame Apoſtle ſpeaketh in the firſt to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> &amp; 18. <hi>When he ſaith, we ſhal not all die, but all ſhall be changed:</hi> thoſe I ſay that then are liuing vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth, ſhal not preuent or goe before thoſe that are dead and turned to duſt and powder in the earth:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:25534:58"/>but as thoſe that are liuing ſhall be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from mortall, to immortall, in the twinckling of an eye (to vſe the Apoſtles words) ſo likewiſe ſhall thoſe of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that are dead be raiſed vp by the power of God, at the voice of the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and being ioyned to their ſoules, both the one and the other (ſaith the Apoſtle) ſhall bee caught vp into the cloudes, to meete the Lord in the ayre, and ſo ſhall euer remaine with the Lord: which he ſpeaketh ſpecially for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the faithful, and therefore addeth this,
<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Comfort your ſelues one another with theſe words.</hi> Thus we ſee how all Nations that is, all people of all the Nations of the world, ſhall be gathered together by the holy Angels, before Chriſt ſitteth in iudgement. The godly with all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels, ſet on his right hand, the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, with all the damned ſpirites, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels ſet on the left, attending and hark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, when that finall and definatiue ſentence ſhal be pronounced. But before we ſpeake thereof, it ſhall not be amiſſe to conſider in a word or two, what ſhall be come of all other things that are now in the world.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Peter</hi> hath reſolued this point
<pb facs="tcp:25534:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:25534:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:58"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:25534:58"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:59"/>already: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he preacheth, that there ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come, and is euen at hand, <hi>the ende of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> things</hi> that is of all mortall things, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the holy Angels are immortall, the damned ſpirits are immortall, the ſoules of men are immortall, and the bodies of all men ſhall then be made immortall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their firſt Creation, for man made himſelfe mortall by ſinne and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, therefore to all theſe ſhall be no end: but the ending of mans body in this world, ſhall be an endleſſe being to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world to come, either to ioy or paine.</p>
               <p>Now as ſaint <hi>Peter</hi> hath told vs, that there ſhall be an ende of this world, ſo likewiſe he telleth vs in the 3. Chapter of his ſecond Epiſtle, how the end ſhal be, &amp; how all things ſhalbe deſtroyed with fire.</p>
               <p>Firſt, he ſaith the world periſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouerflowen of water.
<note place="margin">2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>But the heauens and the earth which are now are kept in ſtore, and reſerued vnto fire againſt the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and of the deſtruction of vngodly men.</hi> By and by he addeth, that when this day of Iudgement ſhall come, the Heauens that are ouer vs, <hi>ſhall paſſe away with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyce, and the Elements ſhall melt with heate, and the earth with all the works that are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhall be burnt vp.</hi> And not contented
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:25534:59"/>with once affirming this, but repeates the ſame againe, that we ſhould neuer forget it in the ende of his admonition ſaying.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seeing therefore that all theſe things,</hi> that is, all worldly and earthly things <hi>muſt be diſſolued, what manner perſons ought yee to be in holy conuerſation and godlineſſe,</hi> Looking for and haſting vnto the comming of the day of God, by the which the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens being on fire ſhall be diſſolued, and the Elements ſhall melt with fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent heate.</p>
               <p>So in fine, we ſee none of theſe things which now we ſee with our mortall eyes, ſhall remaine permanent &amp; durable, but all muſt bee conſumed and diſſolued with fire, which may teach vs not to put confidence in any thing in this world.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding, ſaith the ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>We looke for a new heauen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay. 65.17</note> and a newe earth according <hi>to Gods promiſe made vnto vs by the Prophet Eſay, wherein dwelleth righteouſneſſe.</hi> But of his wonderfull and heauenly renewing, as it is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed vnto vs in the Scripture particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly: ſo it ſhould bee from my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to make any ſearch thereof curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly: ſeeing my text onely leadeth
<pb facs="tcp:25534:60"/>we to ſpeake of the deſtruction, and not of the reſtoring of all things.</p>
               <p>Onely let the godly content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with that diſcourſe, which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle Saint <hi>Paule</hi> maketh in the eight to the <hi>Romanes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom 8.19.20.</note> where he exhorteth the faith full ioyfully to indure all the afflictions of this life which are nothing in value comparable to the glory which at that day ſhall be reuealed vnto them. For ſaith he, <hi>The feruent deſire of the Creature waiteth when the ſonne of God ſhal be reuealed. Becauſe the Creature is ſubiect to vanitie not of it owne will, but by reaſon of him which hath ſubdued it vnder hope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Becauſe the Creature alſo ſhall be deliuered from the bondage of corruption, into the glorious libertie of ohe ſonnes of God:</hi> for we knowe that euery <hi>Creature groneth alſo and trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in paine together vnto this preſent: and not onely the creature,</hi> but we alſo which haue the firſt fruites of the ſpirit, euen we doe ſigh in our ſelues waiting for <hi>the adoption euen the redemption of our body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus hauing hitherto briefely noted how Chriſt ſhall come at the laſt day in glory, attended on with all his holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, how he ſhall ſit vpon the ſeate of his glory, how all Nations ſhall be gathered
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:25534:60"/>before him by the voice of a Trumper, ſounded by an Arkangell, how the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ſhal ſeparate the good from the bad, placing the godly on his right hand, and the wicked on his left hand. Let vs laſt of all conſider of that great doome, and irreuocable ſentence, which the Iudge of heauen &amp; earth ſhal then pronounce, from whom by no meanes they may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale.</p>
               <p>The ſentence that ſhall bee giuen at that day is very ſhort, it is but two words in our tongue, <hi>Come yee, Goe yee,</hi> in the Latine both words are included in one, <hi>Venite,</hi> there is <hi>Venite, come yee,</hi> and in the end of <hi>Venite,</hi> is <hi>Ite, Goe yee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord will make a ſhort accompt vpon the earth ſaith the Apoſtle in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. But I know it wil be ſaid, that Chriſt doth vſe more words, and a very long diſcourſe in that 25. of <hi>Mathew,</hi> then <hi>Venite, &amp; Ite.</hi> It is true he doth ſo, but I am of opinion, that he doth vſe them ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to inſtruct vs while we be liuing, and before we come vnto Iudgement, then to teach vs that we ſhall haue ſo long a ſpeech with him at that time of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding, ſeeing Chriſt for
<pb facs="tcp:25534:61"/>our ſakes hath vouch ſafed to remember the ſame vnto vs. Let vs for Chriſt his ſake conſider of them as that they may neuer be forgotten of vs when our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in that place hath tolde, that the ſon of man ſhall come vnto Iudgement, in his glory, with all his holy Angels, and being ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vpon the ſeate of his glory, all Nations ſhall be gathered before him, the faithful ſheepe on his right hand, and the ſinfull Goates on the left hand, he preſently addeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then the King ſhall ſay vnto them on his right hand,
<note place="margin">Math 25. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>4.</note> that is,</hi> to the faithfull, <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my Father inherite yee the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome prepared for you from the foundation of the world.</hi> Contrariwiſe, the ſame King ſhall ſay vnto them on his left hand, that is, to the wicked and vngodly: <hi>Goe yee curſed or depart from me yee curſed into euerlaſting fire which is prepared for the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell and his angels.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er. 41.</note>
               </p>
               <p>With what words, I beſeech you could our Sauiour more perſwade vs to haue regard how we liue in this world then by propoſing vnto vs theſe two co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences? the one ſo ful of ioy &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort as no tongue can expreſſe. The other ſo full of griefe &amp; horror as no hart can thinke.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:25534:61"/>That the King pronounceth firſt the ſentence of bliſſe, it noteth his goodnes &amp; bountifulnes inclined rather to grace and mercy, then to rigor and Iuſtice: if we had but ſo much grace and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as to accept of it before it be too late.</p>
               <p>That he vſeth this ſingular worde of comfort, <hi>Come yee,</hi> it noteth the ardent loue and affection that our Sauiour bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to his ſheepe, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath purchaſed with his own bloud: therefore he giueth ſo great a charge vnto thoſe, whom he hath appointed Paſtors ouer them in this life, to feede his ſheepe, and to haue care of them in the wilderneſſe of this world, that none of them be deſtroyed or loſt, through their negligence; if they be, their bloud will he require at their ſhepheards hands.</p>
               <p>That he calleth them the <hi>bleſſed of his Father,</hi> it noteth that they are beloued of god, &amp; before ordained vnto this bleſſing: it highly commendeth Gods free grace &amp; fauour, not mans merit or deſeruing.</p>
               <p>That he biddeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>to poſſeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the kingdome</hi> not any longer to expect a kingdome, it noteth the difference betwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the ſtate of the faithfull here and that is to come
<pb facs="tcp:25534:62"/>here we enioy all by faith &amp; hope, their faith and hope ſhall ceaſe, when we are put in poſſeſſion of that we hoped for, and haue receiued the end <hi>of our faith, the ſaluation of our ſoules.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo it is a great incouragement vnto the godly in this life, to waite with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence till their pilgrimage be ouer paſt to contemne and deſpiſe all the glory of this world, ſpecially if the Diuell offer it to eſteeme all things as dung, and as droſſe, in reſpect of this glorious king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which they ſhall be bid to poſſeſſe. That he ſaith poſſeſſe the kingdome <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared</hi> it noteth that it is a kingdome not merited or deſerued by vs.</p>
               <p>That he ſaith laſtly, that it is a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome prepared for <hi>you before the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world,</hi> it ſheweth that God knew vs, loued vs, cared for vs, before we were, that as he made a world for vs, to liue in, before he made vs to liue; ſo he orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a heauenly kingdome for vs to liue in, after we are dead before we died.</p>
               <p>What a good God is this, how can we want any thing if we truſt in him, and call vpon his name. God hath giuen vs his Sonne, with his Sonne a Kingdome, what more can we deſire.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:25534:62"/>God giue vs his grace to take this Cup of Saluation thankfully, as by the Prophet we are exhorted.</p>
               <p>Contrariwiſe, that Chriſt ſaith to the wicked on his left hand, <hi>Depart,</hi> it noteth his hatred and deteſtation of ſinne and ſinners that doe not repent as he faith in another place, <hi>I know you not, depart from me all yee workers of iniquitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Chriſt ſaith <hi>depart from me,</hi> it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that they appertaine not vnto him, neither are of his fold or family, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer were; for thoſe whom he once loueth he loueth to the ende. That he ſaith <hi>yee curſed</hi> it ſheweth the miſerable eſtate, of them that appertaine now vnto Chriſt, howſoeuer wicked men flatter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in this world: they are moſt accurſed in the ſight of God and his Angels; they are curſed while they liue, curſed when they die, and curſed after death: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore like curſed creatures, as they were before they come vnto Chriſt, they are commaunded to depart from his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, vnto the place of the damned.</p>
               <p>That Chriſt ſendeth them <hi>into euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fire,</hi> it noteth both the horror of the puniſhment, and the continuance of the paine, neuer to haue end: <hi>in hell ther is no
<pb facs="tcp:25534:63"/>redemption,</hi> Laſtly, that Chriſt ſaith, that this endleſſe paine and puniſhment was prepared for the <hi>diuell and his angels</hi> it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not (as ſome would haue it) that it was not alſo prepared for the wicked, but rather ſignifieth that the wicked ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine vnto the diuell, whoſe children they are, as ſaith Chriſt, <hi>yee are of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the diuell,</hi> ſeeing they are adiudged to the ſame place of torments with the diuel when they are dead, whoſe ſeruants they are while they liued.</p>
               <p>Thus haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e heard the ſum of both ſentences, which being once pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, the tongue of men and Angels, is not able to expreſſe, the wayling &amp; wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, howling &amp; crying, of theſe curſed creatures, that ſhall be iudged to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, nor yet the vnmeaſurable ioy and conſolation of the faithfull.</p>
               <p>The one conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned ſo euerlaſting tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, the other receaued into euerlaſting glory. The which entence being thus paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that glorious Seſſions will be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: the griefe of the damned a thouſand time in creaſed, in ſeeing and beholding the faithfull and godly whom they euer hated, to be caried by the Angels into the endles ioyes of eternal bliſſe, the diuels in the meane while prepared, to carry thoſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:25534:63"/>curfed Caytiues with thee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, into the botto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe gulfe, of their infernall confuſion.</p>
               <p>But here happily, ſome will ſay that I do not well to conceale that which our Sauiour addeth at the end of thoſe ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſaying, to the <hi>faithful, I was hungry,
<note place="margin">Math. 42.</note> &amp; ye gaue me meate, I thirſted, &amp; ye gaue me drinke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Truely, if you will giue the leaſure to read it, I would very gladly touch it, with this caueat, that we do not imagine thoſe good works to be the cauſe of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: ſeeing as hath beene ſaid already, our ſaluation was prepared for vs, before we can worke at all: much more before we could doe good works: neither will this ſhift of the ſcholeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the turne, to ſay that God did happily foreſee thoſe good works that we would doe, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore prouided a reward for them, before they were done: ſo deſirous are thoſe Merit-mongers, to haue God beholding vnto them for their good works.</p>
               <p>But why can they not as wel ſee, if they would not cloſe their eyes of purpoſe: that God ſaid long agone,
<note place="margin">Gen 6.</note> 
                  <hi>all the imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of mens hart are euil continually.</hi> And when that God looked downe from heauen of purpoſe to ſee the children of men, he <hi>ſawe none that was good, no not one.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:64"/>And why can they not heare the Apoſtle ſay,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſ. 2.10</note> that <hi>God hath created vs vnto good works, that we ſhould doe them.</hi> Chriſt himſelfe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing when <hi>yee haue done all that yee can,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 17.</note> ſay yee are vnprofitable ſeruants, yee haue done, but what was your duetie to doe.</hi> To let paſſe all other places of ſcripture, and all the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of the Apoſtles: which may ſerue as ſo many Rams, to beate downe to the ground this diueliſh doctrine of popery.</p>
               <p>But now let vs heare what Chriſt ſaith to the faithfull, and what reply the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full make vnto him: Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I was an hungred, and yee gaue me meate: I thriſted, and yee gaue me drinke: I was a ſtranger, and yee lodged me: I was naked, and yee clothed me, I was ſicke, and yee viſited me, I was in priſon, and yee came vnto me.</hi> The faithfull anſwere preſently they neuer ſawe him in that caſe, neither euer did any ſuch thing vnto him. But Chriſt ſheweth his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſaith in <hi>as much as yee haue done it vnto the poore with you, yee haue done it to me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here then we are taught firſt the care that Chriſt taketh of the poore, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is done vnto them if they be godly, it is done vnto him.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the cauſe wherefore he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:25534:64"/>ſome rich, and leaueth others in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, whom he loueth moſt dearely, that he may exerciſe the patience of the one, and try what charity is in the other.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that the faithfull in a holy kinde of humilitie ſeeme either to deny or at leaſt leſſen and extenuate the good workes they haue done; we are taught hereby, that in doing of good, ſpecially in giuing of our Almes, <hi>The right hand muſt not know what the left hand doth.</hi> So far muſt we be from boaſting, that we muſt euen diſtruſt and doubt in our ſelues, that we haue not diſcharged our duetie in that behalfe, as wee ought to doe as who knowes the beſt of vs all come farre to ſhort.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, we are taught how excellent things they are, if they be done in faith, and in the feare of God: to feede the hungry, to clothe the naked: not that all the workes of mercy &amp; charitie are here numbred, or any certaine number obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but onely theſe few are named, for examples ſake, to ſhewe vs that mercy muſt be vſed, where mans miſery doth neede it, and withall we muſt make a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, betwixt thoſe dueties which we doe as we are men, and thoſe that we do,
<pb facs="tcp:25534:65"/>as we are Chriſtian men: therefore what ſoeuer good we doe vnto gods Saints we muſt do it in, &amp; for Chriſts ſake: though it be but a gift of a cup of cold water in his name, we ſhall not looſe our reward (though not rewarded of merite &amp; deſar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but of mercy &amp; grace) God of his mercy make vs mindful of thoſe dueties, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them as he ſhall enable vs, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we muſt looke for no mercy at his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, but ſhal be ſure to heare that which ſhall be pronounced to them on the left hand, <hi>I was an hungred, &amp; ye gaue me no meat: I thirſted and ye gaue me no drinke:</hi> And then though we wil excuſe the matter neuer ſo cunningly, &amp; alleadge that we neuer ſaw Chriſt hungry, or a thirſt, becauſe wee would not ſee Chriſt in his poore mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, being in that caſe, becauſe we wold ſhut vp our compaſſion fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the poore, &amp; turne our eyes from our owne fleſh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our religion was onely but in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion, no liuely fruits of faith budding foorth: becauſe we would not viſite the widdow &amp; the fatherles in their aduerſity, and keep our ſelues vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>potted of the world, nay becauſe while we liued in this world: we did wrong the widow, &amp; the fatherleſſe, and grind the faces of the poore: therefore as we haue done, ſo ſhal
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:25534:65"/>it be done vnto vs: the ſame meaſure that we ſhall meaſure vnto others, the ſame ſhal be meaſured vnto vs againe <hi>There ſhal be Iudgement mercileſſe,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>am. 2.13.</note> to him that ſheweth no mercy: but mercy contrariwiſe ſhall reioyce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Iudgement.</hi> Finally, our Sauiour repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the ſumme of both ſentences again, leſt happily we haue for gotten them: as too of en we do.
<note place="margin">Math 25. vlt.</note> 
                  <hi>And theſe (ſaith Chriſt) ſhal go into euerlaſting paine, &amp; the righteous into life eternall.</hi> That is, thoſe graceleſſe Goats, thoſe mercileſſe miſers, thoſe miſerable miſcrea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, that haue had no feare of God before their eyes, no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion on their brethren that haue hated to be reproued, that haue had their whole ſwing in ſin, &amp; wearied themſelues in vanitie, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all be ſent packing into euerlaſting paine.</p>
               <p>But the righteous, that is, thoſe that haue apprehended the righteouſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſſe of Chriſt, Ieſus by a true &amp; liuely faith, &amp; haue repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted &amp; indeuoured to leaue ſin, before ſin leaue them, thoſe that haue brought forth the timely fruits of repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, with an ardent zeale vnto Gods glory, and a burning charitie vnto their poore brethren theſe ſhall goe preſently into life eternall: by which two words <hi>life
<pb facs="tcp:25534:66"/>eternall and paine euerlaſting</hi> is certainely noted the perpetuall and endleſſe conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of the ioyes of the godly and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the damned in the world to come neuer to haue end.</p>
               <p>But it may be, ſome will ſay, that we poſt on with theſe two ſentences to faſt, Chriſt will vſe a greater moderation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he proceede to ſentence, there is mention made in the ſcripture of bookes that muſt be opened.</p>
               <p>It is true indeede, <hi>Daniell</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Iudgement was ſet;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 7.10.</note> and <hi>before ſentence is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, the bookes are opened.</hi> Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> likewiſe in the <hi>Reuelation</hi> when he ſawe the dead both great and ſmall ſtand before God, ſaith, <hi>that the bookes were opened, and an other booke was opened,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 20.12.</note> which he calleth <hi>the booke of life.</hi> The Booke of life I take to be the hidden and vnreueiled knowledge of God, concerning thoſe whom he hath appointed to life and ſaluation. And this Booke is not for me, or any mortall man to looke into: by the other bookes, I ſuppoſe are meant the conſciences of all men in generall, and of euery one in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular which ſhall either excuſe, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe vs at that day. Theſe bookes alſo are very ſecret bookes layed vp in the Cloſet
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:25534:66"/>of euery mans hart. And I haue no skill to read in any of them, but in mine own. Indeede they are bookes of accompt, which euery one muſt be careful to keep, vntill this great day of reckoning come. They are alſo Bookes of record, wherein are written all the things that we haue done in this life whether they be good or euill: and at that day ſhall be layed open in <hi>Facie curiae,</hi> in the viewe, and open fight of men and Angels. Then ſhall be verified that ſaying of our Sauiour in the Goſpell: <hi>Nothing is ſo ſecret that ſhall not be euident, neither any thing hid that ſhall not be knowen, and come to light.</hi> Wherefore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth euery one to haue a ſpecial regard of theſe bookes, and to couet euermore with the Apoſtle to haue a cleare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is as the wiſe <hi>Man</hi> ſaith, <hi>a continuall feaſt,</hi> for if our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences condemne vs not, then haue we boldneſſe towards God, ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn:</hi> contrariwiſe, ſaith that Apoſtle, <hi>If thy hart and conſcience accuſe thee,</hi> God is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then thy hart and knoweth all things. If thy conſcience be againſt thee, it will be <hi>Mille teſtes,</hi> more then a thouſand wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</p>
               <p>Theſe conſciences of ours beloued,
<pb facs="tcp:25534:67"/>which now we thinke we can ſtretch and ſtreine as we pleaſe, are the bookes of record, which then muſt be opened: ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to excuſe or condemne vs: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſentence ſhal be giuen accordingly.</p>
               <p>My admonition therefore is, that all buſineſſe laied aſide, the next priuate lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that euer we haue, let vs ouerwiew againe and againe, theſe bookes of rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning, &amp; ſee that the accompts be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: where there is any deſect, let it be amended without delay: for God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, how ſoone theſe bookes may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for to be opened, and then it will be too late to amend, the leaſt blot, or fault that is in them.</p>
               <p>Let vs follow the counſell of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to accuſe and condemne our ſelues in this world, that ſo we may be acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and not condemned in that feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iudgement. And this I hope may ſuffice to be ſpoken of this matter, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the glory of Chriſt his comming and the maner of the Iudgement</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:25534:67"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The eight Chapter wherein is intreated of</hi> Sobriety, Watchfulneſſe, <hi>and</hi> Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T might ſeeme that ſaint <hi>Peter</hi> had very well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged his dutie in fore warning the world of the danger to come, towards the end thereof: in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>ende of all things is at hand.</hi> But that holy Apoſtle like a carefull Phiſition not contented to warne vs, that we fall not into a dangerous diſeaſe of ſecurity: doth with all readineſſe &amp; diligence preſcribe vnto vs a maruellous good medicine, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are alreadie ſicke in that diſeaſe: &amp; the ſame may alſo ſerue as a pure pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatiue to keepe thoſe that are more ſound, from the infection thereof: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting vs vnto ſobrietie, watchfulneſſe and prayer. As if he ſhould ſay, The end of all things is at hand, and the Iudge is at the doore ready to take vengeance, of all vngodlineſſe and intemperancie. <hi>By yee therefore ſober.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The day of his comming is altogether vncertain. <hi>Be ye therfore vigilant &amp; watchful.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:68"/>If this be to hard for fraile fleſh to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, fly <hi>vnto Prayer,</hi> which maketh the hardeſt things eaſie to be done.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be yee ſober,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4 7.</note> and watch vnto Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of either of theſe three briefely. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie, Watchfulneſſe, and Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of <hi>Sobrietie,</hi> or <hi>Temperancie,</hi> we haue heretofore ſpoken ſufficiently I truſt, to inſtruct them that are godly and in loue with that vertue, it is the fourth linke in Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Chaine. In this place there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by way of digreſſion, I will indeuor to ſpeake briefely of <hi>Intemperancy</hi> the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bane &amp; cut-throate of all Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and Pietie, and a moſt cruell enimie vnto all good gouernement and policie.</p>
               <p>There is a ſaying, <hi>Nemo laeditur niſi a ſe ipſo,</hi> euery man is the worker of his owne woe: I pray God the generall <hi>Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancie</hi> of this land doe not viper-like eate out the bowels thereof.</p>
               <p>The ſtinging of a Viper they ſay at the firſt, doth yeelde a certaine tickling de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to all the outward ſences; but aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoone as the infected bloud comes to the hart, preſently the body is in daunger of death: what pleaſing delight is dayly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in <hi>Intemperancie</hi> by all the ſences, I meane by all ſorts and ſexts of people in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:25534:68"/>this land, as in other places of the worlds it may better be felt then ſeene: when <hi>Paule</hi> had but one viper on his hand,
<note place="margin">Acts. 28.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> all the ſtanders by looked that hee ſhould haue fallen downe dead preſently. But this countrey being ſtung with the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome of vipers, I meane all kinde of fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy vices, not in the band onely, but in euery part of the body, yet no man fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the ruine or fall thereof.</p>
               <p>Moſt true it is, that we which li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in the latter end of this laſt age of the world liue in the time, and vnder the climate of all intemperancy, I hope the end is the neerer at hand to redreſſe all that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe: my minde is not, and if my minde would ſerue time would not ſuffer me, particularly to point out all the ſinnes of intemperancy, that abonnd at this day euery where among vs.</p>
               <p>There are foure cardinall ſinnes vpon the which alſo the reſt doe hang, <hi>Pride, Couetouſneſſe, Whooredome, Drunkenneſſe:</hi> which for their ſwiftnes in running ouer the world, may well be compared to the foure wheeles of the diuels chariot, in the which chariot, he daily carrieth cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loads of ſoules into hell. Theſe ſinnes together with the other ſinnes of <hi>Sodome,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:69"/>tumble in one on anothers backe, like the waues of the Sea: there is neither meane nor meaſure kept in any of them. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leaſt I ſhould ſlaunder any with the truth in drinking, they ſay, they haue Law as ſtrong as the Lawe of the <hi>Medes,</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> that euery one muſt drinke by meaſure: but without any meane: they muſt drinke off al their meaſure, and leaue none: yea I heare, and I haue onely heard of it, that our new dubd ale knights whereof we haue great ſtore in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, inough to ranſack any city in Spain, if they were vnarmed of their Ale, &amp; well marſhalled, doe in their dayly drinkings to their meaſure of drinke, adde a certain ſet number of words, which may bee ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the toſſepots watch-word, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in not onely take their delight, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them ſpend their whole thrift at the Ale-houſe, leauing their wiues &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milise alone vncarde for: ſo they may ſit ſinging &amp; ſwinging themſelues in good Ale, from morning to night, it is all that they care for: and all the good or rather euil they deſire to do except it be, alſo to raile at thoſe that be good, and that are wont to reprooue them for this their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſtlineſſe. This meaſurable drinking or
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:25534:69"/>rather vnmeaſurable and vnreaſonable quaffing, &amp; carrowſing, whereof I haue alſo ſpoken in the firſt Chapter, will, nay already doth, begin to breed a great ſcarcity of Corne and grayne in our Countrey. It cannot be denied, but that there are already many good lawes in force to puniſh thoſe dayly drunkards: but neuer worſe executed then at this day: and ſome are of good hope, that there ſhall be ſtraiter and more ſeuere Lawes prouided againſt drunkenneſſe.</p>
               <p>For I verily thinke, (and I wiſh experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence prooue it not to bee true) that drunkenneſſe is more hurtfull and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to this Common-wealth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee liue, then common theft, and therefore I pray God to put it into the harts of all good Common weales men, ſpecially thoſe that are in high places, and authoritie to vſe all good meanes for the redreſſing thereof: and before better or ſtraiter Lawes be enacted to giue ſtraiter charge to all other inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our officers, to execute with all ſeueritie, as in a matter of great neceſſity appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, the lawes of our land already proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, which hitherto of a long time haue
<pb facs="tcp:25534:70"/>bin very much neglected at leaſt in ſome quarters of this Countrey, which will ſurely grow to a greater diſeaſe then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinke off, if it bee not the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner cured: which thing hath cauſed me often to ſpeake, and now to write more againſt this vice of drunkenneſſe both here, and in the firſt Chapter, then many happely will thinke it fit and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient to be ſpoken of in ſo ſmal a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe: howbeit if my words preuaile any thing to the killing of this ſtinging viper drunkenneſſe, I will confeſſe, I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken inough: if nothing, that I haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten too much, except for the diſcharge of mine owne conſcience. And as for the three other capitall vices of intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancie, <hi>Pride, Couetouſneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Whooredome,</hi> I thinke they may be compared to the heads of <hi>Hydra,</hi> for euery head that is cut off by the ſword of the Preachers (for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther puniſhment there is little or none) there ſpring vp an hundred in the place, in ſuch ſort that Preachers are almoſt we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried any longer to floriſh their ſwords of Gods word to cut downetheir ſinnes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it would pleaſe the godly Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to draw out of their ſheathes or ſcabbards their ſharpeſt ſwords of Iuſtice
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:25534:70"/>which in particular Sheathes, I feare are waxen ruſtie for want of vſe: and ſo to ioyne their armies and forces together to kill or at leaſt to keepe downe, thoſe monſtrous <hi>Hydras,</hi> which otherwiſe are like to ſpoyle &amp; deuoure this little land.</p>
               <p>Let it therfore be looked vnto betimes, for feare we repent too late, for there is no daunger compared to that daunger which is not feared.</p>
               <p>Citties, and Countreyes, Townes, and Villages, doe euery where ſtinke with theſe filthy and beaſtly ſinnes, <hi>Pride, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe, Whooredome, Drunkenneſſe: Pride,</hi> muſt needs haue <hi>Couetouſnes</hi> as a miſtreſſe to maintaine her: and <hi>Drunkenneſſe</hi> muſt haue <hi>Whoredome</hi> and <hi>Lechery</hi> for a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid to attend on her: <hi>Sine Cerere, &amp; Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho friget Venus,</hi> Wine and women, make many men runnagates: <hi>Pride,</hi> and <hi>Riot,</hi> cauſeth many to ſell their Patrimonies. <hi>Couetouſneſſe</hi> is the roote of all euill, and neuer deeper rooted then at this day in the harts of wicked worldlings: whoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, fornication and Sodomitrie, to ſpeake nothing of prophaning of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both, blaſphemies, ſwearing, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury, are ſinnes that dayly cry vnto the heauens for puniſhment.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:71"/>Theſe, theſe ſinnes of intemperancie, haue almoſt expeld out of our coaſtes all loue, faith, and fidelitie: and it is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be feared, except we repent and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend our liues ſpeedily, that the heauie wrath of God will fall vpon vs ſhortly, in a more generall maner then heretofore.</p>
               <p>As for the particular puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, what hart ſo hard is there, that cannot rue eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where to heare the moſt lamentable cries and pittifull mones that are made in euery part of this land for the moſt ſtrong &amp; vnheard of fires and burnings, which not caſually as heretofore, but by all probabilities, and by the confeſſion of many, immediatly ſent downe from the heauens vpon many townes in this Land within theſe few yeeres (I may ſay moneths) burning and conſuming moſt ſtrongly, not onely mens houſes, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo their corne, cattell, and ſubſtance, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing almoſt to be ſaued, where theſe fearefull fires haue once aduentured, wherein alſo, which is moſt lamentable, many men, women, &amp; childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, haue been burned into aſhes, &amp; the flames not to be quenched, vntil it hath vtterly conſumed that for which it was ſent: which doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> doth preach vnto vs better then any
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:25534:71"/>tongue can vtter or pen deſcribe, that the God of heauen is grieuouſly offended for thoſe ſins of intemperancy, &amp; for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of his word, which now raigneth e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uery where among vs. And what elſe may theſe fearefull fiers perſwade vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but that the euerlaſting fiers are alſo at hand to burne the world for ſinne, and after all ſinfull men that will not be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in that burning lake, that neuer ſhal be quenched.</p>
               <p>Here alſo we might call to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance and I would to God there were ſome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue made thereof, that we might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them, how many and ſundry wayes within theſe few yeares, God hath and yet doth not ceaſe to forwarne vs of his wrath extraordinarily, and as it were from heauen.</p>
               <p>What a peale of ſhot was that in the yeare, 1588. which did ring the land throughout, to waken them that were a ſleepe in ſecurity, but rumors of warres nor warres it ſelfe, will not warne vs, not make vs to beware. But this noiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhot you ſay was but a beating of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> about vs &amp; could not come neare to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vs. Well be it ſo, yet giue God the pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> that kept it from vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:72"/>But if that noye doe nothing mooue vs, becauſe it was but round about vs: what ſay yee then to theſe terrible thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that we haue had, and heard theſe late yeares, yea this laſt yeare, which made euen the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as it were to crack aboue vs, beſides many extraordinarie winds and tempeſtes?</p>
               <p>And alſo what thinke yee of the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Earthquakes ſeene and felt in many quarters of our Countrey, as elſe where? as if the Center of the earth would ſinke vnder vs, and as though it were ouer bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened with our ſinnes of intemperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: yet if theſe things cannot moue vs, becauſe the thunder you wil ſay was ouer our heads, and the Earth-quake vnder our feete, what yet will yee ſay to thoſe hoate thunder-bolts? which that angry <hi>Iehouah</hi> did caſt downe from heauen, and killed many cattell in our Countrey:
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> to ſpeake nothing of people: and will you thinke any thing of him? that in the midſt of this laſt Summer, did giue haile for raine, yea, ſuch haile in quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie and bigneſſe, as it is incredible to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>, as great and as fearefull haile, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe, as euer fell in the land of <hi>Aegypt.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, alſo with theſe hailes he ſent flames
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:25534:72"/>of fire in our land, and with the force of that haile, brake downe many trees or boughes of trees, and deſtroyed much corne and graine in our coaſtes, beating it into the ground, as dung and ſtubble, ſo that neither corne nor ſtraw, was to be ſaued where this ſtorme did fall.</p>
               <p>Theſe are no fables, neither would I put them into theſe papers: if I knew it not to be true, many can ſweare it, as I haue ſaid it.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Pharaohs</hi> hart is ſtill hardened: &amp; Engliſh Aegyptians will not be warned. Theſe things, ſay they, haue paſſed, but in ſome places, and haue done little harme in reſpect of a general calamitie: to make the worſt of it ſay ſome, it hath hurt and ſpoyled but ſome priuate mens goods, and cattell, or corne, their bodies and liues haue beene ſpared. Thanke we the goodnes of God for that, &amp; learne with all, that the diuell had firſt his commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion graunted for to deſtroy <hi>Iobs</hi> goods,
<note place="margin">Iob. 1.6.7</note> cattell, and children, that pleaſed him not; he came for a newe commiſſion to the King of heauen for to touch his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, he obtained it alſo: at length no doubt would haue come for a third, for his life, if <hi>Iob</hi> had not been very holy, full
<pb facs="tcp:25534:73"/>of patience and pietie.</p>
               <p>But here let vs pauſe a while; haue wee had indeed no generall calamities fallen vpon our country within theſe few years, and haue our bodies alwayes beene ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? indeed we are very forgetful, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if it be any thing that may bee good for our ſoules,</p>
               <p>What then I beſeech you was that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and vnuſuall plague and peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which in more then poſthaſt paſſed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough all this land in a very ſhort time, which brought newes of the Portingall action? And it is thought, there was not any cittie, towne or parriſh almoſt in England, which heard not the ſounde of this packeds horne, albeit wee haue now forgotten it: you may alſo call to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance if you pleaſe, that direfull dearth of corne and grame, that followed hard almoſt to the heeles of this peſtilentiall peſt, as though the other had not done his meſſage ſufficiently enough: ſuch an vnmercifull dearth I thinke was neuer heard of in the memory of man to be in this land, ſpecially ſeeing the price of corne was ſo enhaunced on the ſudden, not ſo much for want of graine in many places, as for want of grace in the heartes
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:25534:73"/>of many hungry helhounds, which were neuer ſatiſfied with any price, vntill they had ſuckt out the bloud of their brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. By means whereof followed ſo fearefull a famine, that ſome were compelled to make bread of ſtraw, other to dye in the ſtreetes for want of food, and ſuch a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly hunger (for ſo ſome haue called it) that the bellies of many people were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable, becauſe they wanted as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that hid treaſur of Gods ſecret bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vpon that bread which they did eate, without which bleſſing, neither bread, though it be called the ſtaffe or ſtrength of man, neither any food els whatſoeuer, is of any more force then a ſtone to feede vs, which when God wil, he is able to turn it into bread for the good of his children, though Chriſt would not do it to tempt God at the requeſt of the Diuell. This doctrine may reach vs while we liue,
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.4.</note> not only to pray for our daily bread, but chief<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to pray for gods bleſſing vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our bread &amp; food which hee giueth, and to praiſe his Maieſtie for it, when we haue receiued it, which the godly call ſaying of grace, both before &amp; after meat, which thing the godles ſcoffe at, &amp; the manners of the multitude wil hardly be brought to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb facs="tcp:25534:74"/>it, though preachers euery where perſwade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to it, &amp; therefore it is to be feared they may ſmart for it again here af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by the like puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of dearth, &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, (which the Lord in his mercy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs from) when God in his Iuſtice ſhall call our vnthankfulneſſe (among many other ſinnes) in remembrance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him.</p>
               <p>And withall, this ſhall not be the leaſt comfort to the godly poore that are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times pinched with penury: if they be well aſſured and perſwaded that euen in their greateſt wants, God wil not faile to prouide for them, if they be faithfull &amp; feruent in prayer,
<note place="margin">1. Kings 17 4. &amp; 12.</note> either to command the Rauens to feed them, as he did <hi>Elias,</hi> either by increaſing the oyle in the Cruſe and the flower in the Pitcher, as the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of <hi>Sareptas</hi> was: or if at any time, as many times it falleth out, they want their dayly bread, which the King of heauen hath commaunded his earthly Stewards to giue them: yet will God ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feed them with ſome other pulſe or ſuſtenance to their good content and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, which was <hi>Daniels</hi> fare, or at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he will ſtay the rage of their hungry bellies, as he did the mouthes of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:25534:74"/>hungry Lyons, that otherwiſe would haue deuoured that Prophet of God. In a word, let not any of Gods children, in any diſtreſſe whatſoeuer doubt of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly prouidence of our God, who hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may pinch vs, but will not ſuffer vs to periſh, <hi>who feedeth the young Rauens that crie vnto him,</hi> and ſhall he not heare his children that truſt in him and call vpon him? Yes verily, let vs be aſſured,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.21.</note> for it is the word of truth, that ſaith, <hi>The righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall neuer be forſaken.</hi> Againe, <hi>The Lyons lacke and ſuffer hunger, but they that feare the Lord, ſhall want nothing that is good.</hi> God make vs faithfull and thankfull, and continue vs in his feare.</p>
               <p>Thus haue we now ſeene, how God hath not ceaſed oftentimes to warne vs to beware of ſinne, and if by thoſe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments already paſſed, we will not learne to be wiſe, but walke on ſtill in the ſtubbornneſſe of our owne harts:
<note place="margin">Leui. 26.</note> then will God <hi>puniſh vs yet ſeuen times more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our ſinnes,</hi> and ſtill will adde ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto ſeuen, as he threatneth, 26. of <hi>Leuiticus,</hi> vntill we be vtterly conſumed in our ſinnes, or haue ſtayed his Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by vnfained repentance.</p>
               <p>And this I hope may ſerue to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:25534:75"/>(as indeed I haue ſpoken much more of this point, then I thought of at the beginning) concerning the ſinnes of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperancie, or any other ſinnes that are contrarie to ſo brietie, and farre vnfitting thoſe people, that truely profeſſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anitie, grounding my ſpeech vpon the exhortation of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> bee ye ſober, and much agreeable to that exhortation of Saint <hi>Paul,
<note place="margin">Titus. 2.11.</note> The grace of God hath appeared, teaching vs to denie all vngodlineſſe and worldly luſtes, and to line ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly, while we liue in this world:</hi> and then we ſhall be ſure to liue for euermore in the world to come.</p>
               <p>The next poynt I promiſed to ſpeak of in this Chapter, is of Chriſtian watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and vigilancie, which is ſo much commended vnto vs in the ſcripture: and is by S. <hi>Peter</hi> oppoſed againſt that great ſinne of careleſſe ſecuritie, in whoſe cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle it is to be feared, moſt people will be lulled a ſleepe, towardes the end of the world: of which point of vigilancie, I will endeuour to ſpeake briefely, and ſo haſten to the laſt point, which is Prayer, whereunto watchfulnes muſt be ioyned.</p>
               <p>And firſt of all, foraſmuch as there is ſo often mention made in the Scripture
<pb facs="tcp:25534:75"/>of this vertue of vigila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy or watchfulnes, it ſhal not be amiſſe for vs, briefly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what it is, that is commended vnto vs by that word: the word is often vſed by our Sauiour himſelfe, ſpecially when he is giuing warning of his ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming. In the 12. of <hi>Luke</hi> he ſaith,
<note place="margin">Luk. 12.35.</note> 
                  <hi>Let your loynes be girded about, and your lights burning, and ye your ſelues like vnto men that waite or watch for their Maiſter, when he will returne from the wedding, that when hee commeth and knocketh, they may open vnto him immediately. Bleſſed are thoſe ſeruants who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord when he commeth, ſhal find waking. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erily I ſay vnto you, he will gird himſelfe about, and make them to ſit downe at table, and will come forth and ſerue them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if hee come in the ſecond watch, or come in the third watch, and ſhall find them ſo, bleſſed are thoſe ſeruants. Now vnderſtand this alſo, ſaith Chriſt, that <hi>if the good man of the houſe had knowne at what houre the theefe would haue come, hee would haue watched, and would not haue ſuffered his houſe to bee digged thorowe.</hi> Be ye alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared therefore, for the Sonne of man will come in an houre when ye think not. The like is ſaid in the Reuelation, <hi>Behold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> I come as a thief,</hi> bleſſed is he that watcheth.
<pb facs="tcp:25534:76"/>And in the 13.
<note place="margin">Mark. 13.34.</note> of <hi>Marke.</hi> The Sonne of man ſaith Chriſt, is as <hi>a man going into a ſtrange Countrey, and leaueth his houſe, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth authoritie to his ſeruants, and to euerie man his worke, and commaundeth the Porters to watch: Watch therefore for yee know not when the maſter of the houſe will come: at euen or at midnight: at the Cocke-crowing, or in the dawning, leſt if he come ſodainely he ſhould find you ſleeping,</hi> By theſe and many other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which willingly for breuities ſake, I omit, it is very euident what it is, that is comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vnto vs, by this word watch, verily nothing elſe but a Chriſtian and carefull heedfulneſſe in our ſeuerall cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, in as much as Chriſt ſaith euery one hath his worke or taske appointed him, as (the Apoſtle ſaith) Let euery one wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is called euen ſo abide with God: Now, like as in Kings and Noble mens houſes, there are diuers and ſundry offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, one is Controller, and another Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ſome ſtanding at the gate, and all other officers labouring in their ſeuerall buſineſſe, wayting for the returne of their Maſter:</p>
               <p>So likewiſe the King of heauen Chriſt Ieſus who for a time, leauing this earthly Countrey, appointed his officers in this
<pb facs="tcp:25534:76"/>world, ſome as Controlers to reproue, ſome as Stewards to prouide for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, ſome as Porters to keep the gate, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as labourers or worke-men in their ſeuerall charges, euery one hath his place where he muſt abide, not idle or ſleepie, but carefull and watching the returne of their Maiſter: bleſſed then ſhall that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant be, whome when his Maiſter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, ſhall find waking, that is, well occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied: but if any of theſe ſhall ſay in a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and contemptuous ſecuritie, <hi>ſurely my Maiſter will defer his comming,</hi> &amp; leauing his owne place or dutie, ſhall begin to ſmite his fellow ſeruants, and to cate and drinke with the drunken, his Maiſter ſhal come in a time when hee is not aware, &amp; ſhall hew him in peeces, and giue him his portion with hypocrites, <hi>there ſhal be wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here hence then we are firſt taught that euery one in this world, aſwel the higheſt as the loweſt, is but an officer vnto the king of heauen, and ſhall one day giue an account of his office.</p>
               <p>Secondly we are here taught, that euery officer hath this peculiarly appropriate vnto him, beſides his office or worke, namely, to watch for the comming of his
<pb facs="tcp:25534:77"/>Lord: and therefore it is, that ſometime we are compared vnto porters, who muſt watch at the gates of our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences, that the diuell ſtep not in to ſteale away our ſoules: ſometimes vnto ſouldiers, who watch in the field, waiting for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of the enemie: ſometimes vnto gueſts, as the olde maner was in the eaſt countrey, to watch for the comming of the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome. And that all are commaunded to watch, leaſt any ſhould think the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves excepted, it is proued by that concluſion of our Sauior in <hi>Marke:
<note place="margin">Mark. 13.37</note> And thoſe things that I ſay vnto you</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>I ſay vnto al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, watch,</hi> which watchfulnes is not oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt naturall ſleepe: for it is a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphoricall ſpeech: but againſt that care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſecuritie, that vſually doth fall vpon all men in their ſeuerall callings.</p>
               <p>Thirdly we are hereby plainly taught, that there ſhould bee none in this world without one office or other, if they will account themſelues ſeruants to this great king: for if they haue not ſome office of their own, they muſt either be idle, which is accompanied with many miſchiefs, or they muſt be il occupied, which is worſe, or they muſt be medling with other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s offices, and dutyes, which is worſt of all.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:77"/>Contrariwiſe here are hardly taxed all thoſe that are called vnto any office, and waite not on their office, whether in the magiſtracy, or in the miniſtry: nay that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuor not to do all the good they can in their offices and places; not hiding, but making ſome gaine of each talent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, all thoſe, whereſoeuer they are placed, either in church or common weale are reproued, what calling ſoeuer they are of, that ſleep in ſecurity, &amp; watch not for the comming of their Maiſter.</p>
               <p>Thirdly thoſe multitudes of people, that liue idle as drones, &amp; haue no calling, but flying fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> place to place, like flies that wil haue a taſte of euery thing, or il occupied like filthy duckes, that euer liue in the puddle of ſinne.</p>
               <p>Fourthly all thoſe are not a little to be blamed, neither ſhall in the world to come eſcape vnpuniſhed, who when they ſhal heare or do any goodnes, are alwaies a ſleepe, or in a ſlumber: but to hurt or beguile their brethren, are euer waking, who are very ready to carrouſe and play, but haue no skill to <hi>watch and pray:</hi> who can moſt willingly ſpend daies &amp; weekes to winne worldly wealth, but thinke one
<pb facs="tcp:25534:78"/>houre in a week to long, &amp; too much, to be ſpared for the winning of their ſoules.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all for a concluſion, as euery one of vs are commanded to ſtand vpon our guard, heedefully to watch the Caſtle of our bodies, wherein the treaſure of our ſoules are encloſed: ſo there is not any one of vs, but haue a ſecret watch within vs continually to waken vs, and to giue vs warning, which is the watchor Clock of our owne conſciences, ſpoken of in the Chapter before: many are deſirous to carry watches or clocks in their boſoms, to giue them warning how time paſſeth away, let vs therfore aboue althings haue regard vnto this watch, which wee carry with vs, whereſoeuer we goe, which doth alwayes runne aſwell by night as by day, and giueth a checke euery minute, and doth neuer ſtand ſtill, except it be to ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and altogether choked with the filth of ſinne.</p>
               <p>This watch will both warne vs, &amp; fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne vs, checke vs, and cheriſh vs: warne vs for any fault paſſed; forwarne &amp; aduiſe vs to auoide dangers to come: check vs, and chide vs, for falling into ſinne: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and cheriſh vs in doing any thing that is good. Theſe watches therefore
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:25534:78"/>are of more worth, then worldlings can account of: they are theſe goodly Geeſe, which alwaies reſt in the Capitol or mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket place of our minds, who with their onely crying, if it be well marked, keepe the cittie of our ſoules from ſacking: to theſe if we hearken diligently, we ſhal not lightly fall into any deadly ſleepe of ſin,
<note place="margin">Acts. 20.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> as the young man <hi>Eutichus</hi> did, though <hi>Paul</hi> continue his preaching vntill mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night: but rather ſhall be ready at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, while the godly ſlumber, and the wicked ſleepe:
<note place="margin">&amp; 12, 7</note> and when the crie is made come vnto the wedding, to ſtrike vs in the ſide, as the Angel did <hi>Peter</hi> in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to wake vs, &amp; warne vs with the wiſe Virgines, to take our lamps, prepared with the oyle of faith, and flaming with the fire of loue in our hands, and ſo to enter in with the Bridegroome, into that great mariage of the Lambe, before it be too late, and the doores be ſhut: at what time it ſhall be ſaid to the fooliſh virgins, that had no oyle in their lampes, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to al the reſt, which would not be maried betimes, by theſe clockes of their conſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, but would ſpend all their time in the ſleepe of ſinne, and ſecuritie, and had no care to watch for the comming of
<pb facs="tcp:25534:79"/>their Maiſter: to all theſe (I ſay) when they ſhall ſtand without, and knocke for mercy, when it is the time of iuſtice, the Iudge himſelfe ſhal ſay vnto them, depart hence, <hi>I knowe ye not, ye workers of iniquitie.</hi> Wherefore let vs hearken betimes vnto this gracious watchword and forewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Saint <hi>Peter, Be yee ſober and watch:</hi> But becauſe hee had learned by his owne experience, the weakeneſſe and frailenes of mans nature, euen thoſe that are beſt minded, and that we (as the Apoſtles in the Garden) are neuer more heauy and ſleepie, then when daungers are neereſt, therefore vnto Chriſtian watchfulnes, he counſelleth to adde faithfull prayer, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Be ſober, and watch:</hi> vnto prayer the like counſell he giueth vs in another place, when he warneth vs of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of our enemie, ſaying, <hi>Bee yee ſober and watch, for your aduerſarie the Diuell, as a roaring Lion, ſeeketh whome he may deuoure,</hi> whome reſiſt (ſaith he) ſtedfaſtly in the faith, the force of which faith muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in our prayers.</p>
               <p>This Leſſon alſo had <hi>Peter</hi> learned of our Sauiour Chriſt, who tolde him and other the Apoſtles, that though the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> were ſometimes <hi>willing,</hi> yet that <hi>the fleſh
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:25534:79"/>is</hi> alwayes <hi>weake,</hi> and therefore willeth <hi>vs to watch and pray.</hi> And the ſame leſſon doth our Sauiour continually teach vs, ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when he telleth vs,
<note place="margin">Mark. 13.</note> that the end of the world is at hand, ſaying, <hi>Take heed, watch and pray, for ye knowe not when the time is.</hi> And againe elſewhere he ſaith, <hi>Watch and pray continually,
<note place="margin">Luk. 21.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> that yee may bee counted worthie to eſcape all theſe things, and that yee may ſtand before the Sonne of man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prayer is a chiefe part of that <hi>Panoplia</hi> or complet harneis, which the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in the ſixt to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ephe. 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> doth charge euery Chriſtian Souldier dayly to put on, or, being put once on, neuer to put it off any more: the reaſon is, becauſe ſo long as we liue in the fielde of this world, we muſt a waies looke our enemie in the face, and neuer turne the backe: Therefore alſo it is that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle hath appointed vs no harneis for our hinder parts. Againe we muſt neuer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arme our ſelues, becauſe there is neuer no truce to be taken with our aduerſarie, who continually ſeeketh to kill vs, as well, or rather, by night, then by day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aſwell in Winter, as in Summer. Again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> becauſe we wreſtle not onely with fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:80"/>and bloud, which are our dayly and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticall enemies, and muſt alwaies bee kept vnder as bond-ſlaues, which natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſeeke to conſpire againſt vs: But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Againſt principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, againſt powers, and againſt the worldly gouernours, the prince of the darkeneſſe of this worlde,</hi> and <hi>againſt ſpirituall wickedneſſes, which are in the high places: For this cauſe wee muſt take vnto our ſelues, the whole armour of God, that wee may bee able to reſiſt in the euill day:</hi> That is euery day when we are temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and hauing many fightes, wee muſt ſtill ſtand vpon our ſtations or guard, <hi>With our loynes girded about with truth, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing on the breſtplate of righteouſneſſe, And our feete ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpell of peace: Aboue all, wee muſt take the ſhielde of faith, wherewith wee may quench all the fierie dartes of the Diuell: We muſt alſo take the hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met of ſaluation, and the ſworde of the Spirit,</hi> which is the word of God: And yet all this is too little, therefore the Apoſtle addeth, <hi>And pray alwayes with all manner Prayer and ſupplication in the Spirit, and watch thereunto with all perſeueranee:</hi> So that wee are taught how wee muſt bee har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed from toppe to toe (as they ſay)
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:25534:80"/>as many as are Chriſtes ſouldiers, they muſt not come naked vnto this fight, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt they onely put on their armor or harnes, but they muſt alſo take wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons in their hands; the ſword of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to ſtrike at the diuel, if he come neare, and the pike of prayer to keepe him off, that he doe not aſſault them: And theſe weapons if the skill of them bee well known, are both offenſiue and defenſiue; they will as well ſticke and wounde the aduerſary, as defend vs from the force of his blowes, when hee ſtriketh towardes vs, yea belieue it (deare chriſtian) though the Diuel play the Lion when hee is not reſiſted, yet if thou come towardes him, as did <hi>Dauid</hi> towardes <hi>Goliah,</hi> with theſe weapons in thine hand, hee wil ſoone flee from thee, as S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, and be afraid of thee, and euen quake for feare,
<note place="margin">Iam 4.7.</note> as doth the Lion at the crowing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a cocke, for as the roaring of a Lion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>righteth the beaſtes of the forreſt, ſo doth the prayers of the faithful profligat or driue to flight the diuels of hel: faithfull prayer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is to be conſidered chiefly in theſe two reſpects; the one is, the great neede and neceſſitie of it, that we may not bee without it: the other is, the fruite &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite
<pb facs="tcp:25534:81"/>that it bringeth with it, if it bee dayly and continually vſed: the neceſſity wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we ſee already, in that it is one of out chiefeſt weapons, wherewith wee muſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore be fighting; if happely at any time the ſword of the ſpirit, which is the word of God bee forgotten behinde, or layed vp in our cloſet, as the ſword of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> was behind the Ephod; and the dore of our remembrance locked, and the key loſt for a time, yet praier muſt alwayes be preſent, and neuer be forgotten behind; therefore it is that wee are ſo oftentimes exhorted in the ſcriptures to pray conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, and alwayes giue thankes for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites receiued, not that we ſhould doe nothing els but pray, but to teach vs that whatſoeuer we doe elſe, either at home or abroad, wee muſt if we pleaſe vſe prayer with it, either publikely or priuately, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in word or in thought, yea the very ſecret groninges of the godly at al times are acceptable vnto God, and to teach vs alſo that euery good thing wee take in hand ſhall proſper the better for prayer, yea thinges <hi>Adiaphora,</hi> thinges indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, yea euen our ſportes and recreation, ſuch as the wicked vſe prophanely, may by the godly be vſed holily by the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:25534:81"/>of praier.
<note place="margin">1. Tim 4.5.</note> 
                  <hi>All things</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>are ſanctified by the word of God and prayer:</hi> that is, as I take it all indifferent thinges, ſuch as in themſelues are neither good nor euill, are ſanctified to the vſe of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, for thinges that are euer good, are euer ſanctified, and thinges that are meerely euill can neuer bee made good, only the euilnes that is in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, may be auoi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded and taken away, and ſo the thing that was euil before, may in a ſort bee changed into goodnes; &amp; all this is done by the word of God and praier, through the mightie working of the holy &amp; ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying ſpirit of God.</p>
               <p>Praier therefore (I ſay) muſt be preſent with the children of God at all times, &amp; <hi>the praiſes of God muſt be in their mouthes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually,</hi> for as a ſouldier without weapon, ſo is a chriſtian without praier, and as water is the life of a fiſh, ſo is praier the life of the fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e: As <hi>Sampſon</hi> was ſoone ouercome by the Philiſtines when hee once cut off his haire, wherin his ſtrength was: ſo theſe diueliſh Philiſtines will ſoon come vpon vs, if once they ſee vs to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect or caſt away praier, wherein our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſtrength conſiſteth. For this cauſe the neceſſitie of praier is not onelie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended
<pb facs="tcp:25534:82"/>vnto vs in ſcripture, by ſundrie precepts,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Pſal. 50.15 Mat. 11.28.</note> as <hi>Call vpon me in the day of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp; I wil hear thee</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>&amp; thou ſhalt prayſe me.</hi> And again, <hi>come vnto me al that tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uel and are heauy loden with the burthen of ſin, I will eaſe ye,
<note place="margin">Mat. 7.7.</note> I will refreſh ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. And ſeeke, aske, knocke,</hi> which teacheth vs that wee muſt continue in praier, and manie ſuch like precepts, but alſo it is moſt of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto vs by example, which is a moſt forcible kind of teaching: what mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth that continual courſe of praier, and the ſpending of whole nightes in praier by our ſauiour, but to commend vnto vs the neceſſitie of praier?</p>
               <p>No ſooner did that good diſciple, who ſoeuer he was deſire our Sauiour to teach his diſciples to pray, as <hi>Iohn</hi> before had taught his, but preſentlie his godlie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is gratiouſlie granted,
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.2.</note> and a moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect paterne and right forme of praier is preſcribed by Chriſt himſelfe, whereby all the praiers of the Saints muſt euer be ſquared, wherein the Lord did not onely teach vs to pray, but preſcribed a forme euermore to be vſed. The Apoſtles ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding him, as al the Patriarkes and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prophetes going before, doe by their ſingular examples, highly commend the
<pb facs="tcp:25534:82"/>ſweete exerciſe of godly praier vnto all Gods children, till the end of the world: and therein is not onely to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the neceſſitie, but alſo the efficacie &amp; fruit of praier, which is the other point that I note.</p>
               <p>Holy <hi>Enoch</hi> the ſcripture ſaieth,
<note place="margin">Gen. 5.24</note> 
                  <hi>He wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with God,</hi> that is, was euer conuerſant, and as it were talking with God by faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full praier, for they that pray faithfully talke with God, as they that reade the ſcriptures deuoutely, God talketh with them:
<note place="margin">Iam. 2:23</note> what ſhall we ſpeake of <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the faithfull, who is called <hi>The friend of God,</hi> God did ſo fauourably heare his praiers that he made vnto him ſo that he was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to feaſt with him at his inſtant intreaty. Of <hi>Iſaack</hi> praying,
<note place="margin">Gen 24.60</note> as ſaieth the Text, <hi>in the field,</hi> when his wife <hi>Rebecca</hi> was ſent by God vnto him:
<note place="margin">Gen: 28.20</note> what of <hi>Iacob,</hi> whoſe praier procured him a proſperous iorney, &amp; preſerued him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all dangers? What ſhall wee ſpeake of <hi>Moyſes</hi> that man of God? whoſe praiers preuailed mightily with the Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſa. 106.33</note> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Lord would haue deſtroied the children of Iſrael at once.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> And of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua,</hi> at whoſe praier, <hi>the Sunne ſtood ſtill in Gibeon, and the Moone in the valley Auieloth,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:83"/>till the Iſraelites were reuenged of Gods enemies: So true is that ſaying of Saint <hi>Iames: The praier of a faithfull man auaileth much,
<note place="margin">Iam. 5.16.17.18.</note> if it be feruent</hi> And propoſeth <hi>Elias</hi> for an example, whoſe inſtant and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full praier, did locke &amp; vnlocke the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s (as it were) wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h a key, that they drop ped no raine, <hi>in three years and ſixe monethes,</hi> and again, at his praier the heauens gaue raine aboundantly. I ſhould bee too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to recite all the examples.
<note place="margin">1. King. 3.9</note> Let <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> be remembred, who praied for wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, rather then for gold, and God gaue him his deſire, aboue all that euer were before him.
<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.30</note> Let not <hi>Sampſon</hi> be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, though he once loſt his ſtrength, as al Gods Saints doe one time or other, more or leſſe, yet as ſoone as he had reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered a little ſtrength againe in a time conuenient, he fell vnto praier, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently pulled downe the houſe, where Gods enemies were aſſembled: Hee kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led more Philiſtines now ſaieth the text, with praier and little ſtrength, then hee did in all the time of his life before, when happely praier was neglected, and he too confident in worldly ſtrength.</p>
               <p>The ſtory of <hi>Daniel</hi> wee know is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, who praied <hi>three times a day to his
<pb facs="tcp:25534:83"/>God,</hi> that is, the God of heauen, at that time alſo, when it was preſent death for him ſo to doe, and ſee how wonderfully God deliuered him from all his enemies, and from the iawes of the Lions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauid a man choſen after Gods own hart,</hi> and a king, though troubled with wars, and other moſt ſerious affaires, yet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got not to pray euening and morning, &amp; at noone tide, and the Lord heard his praier: his praiers and his praiſes in the pſalmes can neuer be praiſed nor peruſed ſufficiently. The Apoſtle in the Actes,
<note place="margin">Act. 2.46.</note> &amp; the Saintes of God aſſemble themſelues together, and continue with one accord in praier, for praier, whether it bee pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like or priuate, muſt be voyde of diſcord: publike diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion hinders very much the publike praiers in the church: a thing greatly to be lamented in our times, and priuate diſcordes let and hinder priuate perſons, at home in their houſes, from thoſe ſweet exerciſes of praier and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God, with <hi>Pſalmes and hymnes and ſpiritual ſongs</hi> in priuate families, as true Chriſtianity requireth. And as <hi>Iames</hi> the Apoſtle exhorteth, if we be in aduerſitie, or in any griefe or neceſſity, then to vſe <hi>that part of praier,</hi> which is called petition,
<pb facs="tcp:25534:84"/>if mercy and in proſperitie, then <hi>to ſing Pſalmes,</hi> which is the other part of praier and thankſgiuing: though I know pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is alſo included in the pſalmes, and giuing of thankes, not ſeldome vſed with out ſinging both in publike, and in priuate, neuertheleſſe they muſt euer be free from diſcord and diſſention.</p>
               <p>Therefore S. <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. pet, 3.7</note> when hee diſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth married couples, to liue without diſcord, he addeth this for a ſpeciall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>that your praiers be not hindered:</hi> for God, to whome onely wee muſt preſent our praiers, by the meanes of Chriſt, not to Saintes or Angels, is a God of peace, therefore onely heareth the praiers of them that be in loue &amp; peace with God and man: with God by faith and true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, with men, by a chriſtian recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation and godly agreement. Therfore <hi>Paul</hi> ſayeth, <hi>Men muſt pray euery where, lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp pure hands without wrath or doubting.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ti. 2, 8</note> Thus did the Apoſtles and ſaints of God in the primitiue church pray faithfully and zealouſly together in loue and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and ſee the fruit and force of their praiers. <hi>The holy Ghoſtfell vpon them, and the places did ſhake oftentimes vnder them,</hi> in token of ioy, and to aſſure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that their
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:25534:84"/>praiers were pleaſing vnto God. But ſtay, let mee marke how I proceede on; I had thought that I had eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> run my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed courſe, &amp; might here haue caſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, but looking better about, I cannot ſee the ſhore, nor the hauen wherein I would willingly harbour.</p>
               <p>By that which hath beene ſpoken, wee may a little perceiue the vſe and neceſſity of praier, and we ſhall bee the better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded thereof by daily trying and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering of our owne weakenes &amp; wants, alſo the daily miſeries &amp; calamities both publike &amp; priuate, which hang ouer our heades, and the mighty force and craftes of our aduerſaries, both ſpirituall and temporall, againſt whome wee muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually fight by praiers, according to the ſaying; <hi>Arma eccleſiae ſunt preces &amp; lacrimae:</hi> The beſt armour and weapons of the faithfull, are praiers made with teares, which teares ſo ſhed are not loſt, for God <hi>will put them vp in his bottle.</hi> By that I ſay, which hath beene ſaid before, the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of praier may partly bee perceiued: but as for the force and efficacy therof, though in the forenamed exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples, ſome thing doe appeare, and the ſweetnes of comfort and contentation, that it daily
<pb facs="tcp:25534:85"/>ſtireth vp in the harts of Gods children, I perſwade my ſelfe they may be far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perceiued, then expreſſed, for what is praier els to them that know how to pray effectually? but euen a moſt famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar talke of man with God, by the meanes of Chriſt. What other thing is praier? but an opening &amp; vnfoulding of our minds vnto God, to make our mones vnto him in all our miſeries, euen as do deare and obedient children, vnto their moſt louing and moſt mercifull father, to pray vnto him for whatſoeuer we want neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for ſoule and body, with full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to be heard, if it be for his glory &amp; our good, and to praiſe his Maieſtie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually for all his benefites.</p>
               <p>And if at any time our praiers ſeeme not to be heard at firſt, as oftentimes it falleth out, then wee are alſo aſſured, that he doth either deny them for our good, and will giue vs better thinges, when it pleaſeth him, or elſe for a time delaieth and deferreth our petition, to the ende hee may the better try our obedience, proue our patience,, and confirme vs in perſeuerance: which three vertues being knit together, make that cable of three twiſtes, which being tied faſt to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:25534:85"/>of faith, can neuer bee broken. God in hearing and graunting our praiers, is like (as S. <hi>Ierome</hi> compares him) vnto a faithfull Phiſitian, that wil ſuffer his ſicke patient to crie long enough, if hee call for things that are hurtful for his health, yet notwithſtanding, hath more care of his good and recouery, then the patient hath of himſelfe and therefore it is, that theſe ſweete ſentences of S. <hi>Auſten</hi> are to be regarded, who ſaieth, <hi>Deus ſaepe non ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> audit ad voluntatem, vt exaudiat ad ſalutem,</hi> God oftentimes doth not heare vs as we deſire, but onely as in his wiſedome, hee knoweth beſt for our health, and for our good. And againe, the ſame father ſaith, <hi>Si non dat ad horam, &amp;c.</hi> if God ſometimes do ſeeme not to heare preſently, it is to exerciſe the petitioners, not becauſe hee diſpiſeth our praiers.</p>
               <p>But what pen is able to expreſſe the profite and pleaſure, the ſweet comforte and conſolation in ſoule and mind, that the children of God do feele in this holy exerciſe of praier, if it bee made with knowledge and conſcience, with faith &amp; feeling, without wrath or doubting, free from hypocriſie, and any popiſh conceit to bee heard for our much babling ſake,
<pb facs="tcp:25534:86"/>againſt which vices our Sauiour doth moſt ſharply inueigh in the 6. of <hi>Mathew.</hi> And the Apoſtle doth plainely reproue that lip-labour, &amp; bibble babble, ſuch as is yet vſed in the Romiſh churches, that is made in an vnknowne tongue, and ſo without knowledge and vnderſtanding, and therefore without fruit and profite: whereof I here giue warning, leaſt any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with theſe follies of Popery, ſhuld thinke themſelues alſo commended that ſpend their whole time almoſt in praying vpon their beades, and in mumbling of their Mattins, and our Ladies Pſalter, as they cal it, which hath neither any ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, nor any godly ſauour in it, but alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether offenſiue vnto God, and moſt da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous for the health of their ſoules: but leauing them that alſo ſin of ignorance, to Gods mercy to be recalled; and their leaders to that iudgement, which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt them, except they ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily repent. Let vs returne to finiſh our diſcourſe, concerning the fruit and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of praier, as well publike as priuate, and the rather I make mention of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique praier, becauſe it is neglected of a great many which otherwiſe thinke themſelues good profeſſors of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:25534:86"/>for I ſpeake not here of open Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſantes, that are worthily blamed, and alſo puniſhed for their indurate obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but I ſpeake onely of thoſe, that will not come to publike praiers, except there bee preaching: how neceſſary it is, that there ſhould be preaching in euery con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, what good man ſeeth not? what good Chriſtian deſireth it not? for it is the beſt externall meanes, to teach vs how to pray, and all other good duties whatſoeuer: but where one wanteth, muſt the other alſo bee neglected? God forbid, mee thinkes there is no reaſon to be yeelded for it, except you will ſay, it is reaſon, that while a man is fighting with his enemie, and his ſword be broken off, or ſtroken out of his hand, he muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore caſt away the dagger too, and ſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer himſelfe to bee killed or ſtabbed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently. Haue we not heard before, that praier is that weapon, that muſt euer bee preſent with vs, both at home &amp; abroad, both in priuate and in publike? they ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (for that is the common excuſe) that will pray at home, or in priuate, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they may and will not come vnto pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like praiers, are like vnto ſome daſtard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25534:87"/>ſouldiers, who while the whole Campe is skirmiſhing, flouriſh their ſwords out a part by themſelues, and yet thinke they haue plaied the men ſufficiently. I ſpeake not againſt priuate praier, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſwade all men vnto it, but I ſpeak onely againſt thoſe, that will not come at publike praiers, where many ſouldiers to gether may doe better ſeruice then a few alone. And alſo by the way, thoſe may be noted, that all the times of publike praier, wil be buſied in their priuate prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as though they were ſouldiers of an other campe: and ſometimes reading or pooring in a booke, and that is vſed of many in time of preaching alſo, as thogh publike praier and preaching were not to be regarded: theſe abuſes therefore, and many other which I cannot ſtand to rehearſe, being auoided and eſchewed, the force and fruit of faithfull and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous praier, as well priuate as publike, will bee the better felt and perceiued of all thoſe that ſhall religiouſly and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully accuſtome themſelues vnto it. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny I know haue written moſt learnedly and excellently of the ſweet fruit and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie of praier, howbeit I perſwade
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:25534:87"/>my ſelfe, that wee may ſay of them, and of all others, that ſhall entreat thereof, as the Samaritanes ſayde to the woman,
<note place="margin">Io. 4.42. 1. King. 10.8.</note> that brought them tidings of Chriſt; and as the Queene of Saba ſayde of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticall ſeruantes of <hi>Salomon,</hi> they do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port moſt rare and ſurpaſſing pleaſure, fruit and commodity, to bee preſent at hand with this moſt ſingular and ſweete exerciſe of praier, yea thinges incredible to be reported, and therefore not to be beleeued of the greater part, but vnto them that haue ſeene <hi>Salomon</hi> in the face, and haue heard the gratious words, that proceed out of his mouth, to them the one halfe is not reported, that they find true by their owne experience, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be expreſſed to others.</p>
               <p>I wiſh therefore euery Chriſtian ſoule, not to thinke to finde the fruite of prayer demonſtrated in paper, but to endeuour dayly to feele the force thereof in themſelues, by practiſe: and then let them tell mee, whether this thing be not true that I haue ſaide. For what thing is there that our ſoules can wiſh or deſire, if it be good for vs, but may be obtained by prayer? What caſe
<pb facs="tcp:25534:88"/>or ſorte ſoeuer we bee in, wee may either bee confirmed or comforted by prayer. What worke or labour is there, which we take in hand, whether of ſoule or bodie, how hard ſoeuer it be, if it bee agreeable to our callings, but may be atchieued by prayer? In time of peace, prayer keepeth vs in ſafety: In time of warre, it getteth vs the victorie. In time of proſperitie, it keepeth vs from pride: In time of aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, it keepeth vs from deſpaire. If wee be in health, we may pray without paine: If wee bee ſicke, pray, and recouer, as did <hi>Hezekiah:</hi> If wee bee rich, prayer encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth our ſtore: If wee bee poore, prayer maketh vs rich, in content and goodnes: If we be in authoritie, wee haue neede to Pray for wiſedome, courage, and grauity: If of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monaltie, for obedience &amp; loi altie: If wee be Paſtors, our prayers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile for the people: If we bee pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, wee muſt pray and prayſe God, for, and with our Paſtors. In a word, prayer is a preſent for a Prince, and is a delight for the painefull plough-man: euery man is delighted with the ſinging of the Nightingale, but no Nightingales ſong is ſo ſweete in the eares of man, as the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:25534:88"/>faithfull prayers of the Saints, are in the eares of our God. Many commend con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, but prayer is the ſoule of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templatiue life. If thou be in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, thou maieſt pray ſecretly: If alone, thou maieſt pray ſweetely: Whatſoeuer thou doeſt, or whereſoeuer thou goeſt, if prayer be thy guide, thou ſhalt bee ſure to proſper. If thou begin to loathe theſe earthly vanities, prayer will bring into thy ſight, the trueſt treaſures: If thou once begin to mortifie thy ſinfull affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, prayer perfumeth thy ſoule with moſt ſweete conſolation and ioy in the holy Ghoſt: As the hill is the way to the mountaines, and the meanes to aſcende vnto it, ſo prayer is the way to mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: As golde, precious ſtones, and marble, doe make the houſes of Kings, ſo praier doth build the temple of Chriſt that he may dwell in our heartes by the holy Ghoſt: As fire doth ſcoure the ruſt of Iron, ſo prayer doth ſcowre &amp; cleanſe our ſoules from the ruſt of ſinne: And as the ioynts of the body are bound toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by nerues and ſinewes, ſo the ſoules of the righteous are eſtabliſhed by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Prayer therefore, for the force and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie
<pb facs="tcp:25534:89"/>thereof, is compared by one, to a forke, that expelleth all euill things from vs, and to a hooke, or crooke, that pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth downe from heauen, al bleſſings, and good things vpon vs. If therefore thy foule ſeeme at any time to be cloyed and clogged in the earthly tabernacle of thy bodie: the windes of prayer will carrie it aboue the cloudes, and conduct thee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the pallace of eternall pleaſure. Pray therefore faithfully, and pray continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and thou ſhalt bee ſure to haue the preſence and aſſiſtance of the glorious Trinitie. Who therefore will not bee in loue with prayer, which pierceth the cloudes, preuaileth with God, proſpereth our affaires, at home, and abroad, by day, and by night, maketh vs beloued of God and his Angels, bringeth ſweete reſt and peace to our bodies, and eternall reſt and tranquilitie to our ſoules: to our great comfort in this life, and to our endleſſe ioy in the worlde to come, when Chriſt Ieſus, our Iudge and Sauiour, ſhall come in the clouds, to make an end of all mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall miſeries: Who bleſſe vs all, and bring vs at that day, into the ſight of God his Father, that we may ſee his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:25534:89"/>which hee had with him, before the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld was made, by the gracious gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of his moſt holy and bleſſed ſpirit. which moſt holy and vndeuidable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itie, one God of moſt glorious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, be rendred, of vs, and all Saints and gels, in heauen, and in earth, all power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d impire, all prayſe and glorie, and thankeſgiuing, from this time forth, and for euer, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
